片名：埃及妖后
于是，当法萨力亚…
And so it fell out that at Pharsalia...
在罗马发生了最惨烈的流血内战
...the great might and manhood of Rome met in bloody civil war...
凯撒的部队打败了庞培的军队
...and Caesar's legions destroyed those of the great Pompey...
凯撒成为罗马唯一的统治者
...so that now only Caesar stood at the head of Rome.
如其他胜战一样他并不觉得高兴
But there was no joy for Caesar as in his other triumphs...
因为无数战死、被埋没…
...for the dead which his legions counted and buried and burned...
或被烧死的军人都是他的同伴
...were their own countrymen.
焚烧罗马士兵尸体产生的黑烟 与臭味同样又黑…
The smoke of burning Roman dead is just as black...
又臭
...and the stink no less.
是庞培希望这样，不是我
It was Pompey, not I, who wanted it so.
希望我所讲的说话 历史会忠实地记下来
Let what I have said be set down.
你们可以站起来
You may stand.
面对我，不要太自愧也不必故作高傲
Do not try and impress me by looking either too penitent or too proud.
身为战场军官你们为了庞培吃尽苦头
As field officers, you fought miserably for Pompey.
你们的士兵可编入我的部队
Men under your command will be permitted to enlist in my legions...
跟罗焉人一样光荣地返回罗马城
...and returned to Rome as Romans.
你们将拥有相同的权力
You shall have the same privilege.
我并非如此宽宏大量 你们将会被监视
I'm not magnanimous. Your names are marked. You'll be watched.
一有叛变或懦夫行为立刻处死
First sign of treachery, you'll be killed.
什么事，弗拉维乌斯？安东尼？
What is it, Flavius? Antony?
哦，是坎尼迪斯 希望你有庞培的消息
Oh, yes. Canidius. With news of Pompey, I hope.
- 凯撒万岁！ - 为我干杯，坎尼迪斯
-Hail Caesar! -Drink that in my name, Canidius.
敬马克安东尼的骑兵 凯撒的左右手
To all Marc Antony's cavalry, Caesar's left wing and right arm.
庞培有什么消息？
What news of Pompey, or what's left of him?
凯撒，庞培逃走了
Pompey's gone, Caesar.
假装成商贩溜走了
Slipped through our fingers, disguised as a peddler.
- 他丢下军队不理 - 逃到哪里？
-Leaving most of his merchandise. -Gone? Where?
听说他事先准备了一艘大船 目的地是埃及
He has a galley waiting at the coast. Provision enough for Egypt, they say.
埃及？很可能埃及人亏欠他很多
Egypt. Possibly. They owe him a great deal.
他会要求庇护，借钱，拖时间
He'll ask for sanctuary. Borrow money, borrow time.
我以为结束了，看来还没有
I thought it was over. It seems it's not.
鲁非欧，问占卜师
Rufio, consult the augurers. I want to know.
庞培有没有胆在埃及见我
In Egypt, will Pompey face me at last?
凯撒不是要返回罗马吗？
But surely Caesar will now return to Rome!
无论如何，我也要去埃及一趟
I must go to Egypt in any case.
托勒密国王舆姊姊打内战
Young King Ptolemy and his sister have a civil war of their own...
想置对方于死地 况且罗马需要粮食
...intent on destroying each other, and in the process, Rome's wheat.
殿下，不需要这么急逼
That cannot be so urgent.
让罗马最后才庆祝
Let the Romans welcome great Caesar properly at last...
凯撒的大胜利
...in this greatest of his triumphs.
庆祝？庆祝什么？
Triumph? Over what?
为谁？
Over whom?
- 坎尼迪斯 - 有什么吩咐，凯撒？
-Canidius. -Caesar?
除了第十和十二军队留下 其余的跟安东尼回罗马
Leave me the 10th and 12th. Antony's to take the rest to Rome.
- 他几时可以起程？ - 随时都可以
-When can he start? -Whenever you say.
那么就立刻起程
Then at once.
安东尼在罗马将会代表我
And in Rome, Marc Antony is to speak for Caesar.
你们不准质疑他的权力！
His authority is not to be questioned.
他的命令就是你的命令
His word will be yours.
凯撒说的就是法律
As always, Caesar's word is law.
那当然
Of course.
提醒他要抓紧兵权 有兵权才有实力
But remind him to keep his legions intact. They make the law legal.
凯撒
Caesar.
尽管凯撒的舰队驶向埃及…
And even as Caesar's galleys sailed the great sea to Egypt...
但是，一如罗马人…
...it was happening that, just as the Romans...
埃及人也是战祸连年
...so the Egyptians made war, one upon the other...
托勒密舆姊姊克莉奥佩特拉
...for young King Ptolemy would no longer share the throne...
不能共享王位
...with his sister Cleopatra...
他将她逐出亚历山卓
...but drove her from the city of Alexandria...
意图将她彻底打败
...and sought to destroy her.
我们正好遇上本星期的墟期
We've arrived on their market day.
平民可以进入皇家禁地
Once a week they're allowed in the royal enclosure.
管他墟期不墟期
Where's the guard of honor for Caesar?
欢迎凯撒的卫队呢？
Some representative of the royal or military?
至少应该有皇室或军方代表 难得一见高贵的凯撒自行穿过市集
We have the privilege of watching Caesar battle through our marketplace.
马撒勒斯！派十二名军官，只准带剑
Marcellus, a dozen front-rank men, swords only.
开一条路直通皇宫
Clear a direct line to the palace steps.
并且保持畅通！
Then as many more to keep it open.
这样正好中了他们的计 不可以对群众无礼
It's precisely what they hope we'd be stupid enough to do: manhandle their people.
既然是墟期我们就来买东西
No. This is their market day, we will go marketing.
- 您说笑吧？ - 我们一路买到皇宫
-You're not serious. -We'll shop our way to the palace.
有带钱吗？ 买东西一律用钱币付款
Have you my money? Everything is to be paid for by coin.
告诉手下将剑收起来，改带钱包
Tell them to put away the swords and carry moneybags.
橄榄…橄榄油
Olives. Oil of olives.
萨姆斯酒
Ah, the wine of Samos.
酒卖多少钱？ 4德拉克马
How much for your wine? Four drachma.
我们要六十瓶
Sixty of your wine for my men.
付钱
Pay him.
付钱啊
你说罗马人会推撞、惹怒群众
You said they'd push the people and make them angry.
怎么没有发生呢？
Why aren't they doing what you said they'd do?
宫廷大臣，回答陛下
Your king has asked a question, Lord Chamberlain.
罗马人自贬身价，陛下
The Romans have degenerated minds, Most High Majesty.
他们行事诡异
They do the unexpected.
其中有一个
Particularly one Roman.
特别奇怪
Master of the unexpected.
可是他们那么少人…
But with so few men.
你们都气宇非凡
You all look so impressive.
每个人都可以当国王
Any one of you could be king.
至高的托勒密国王
His Divine Majesty, my Lord Ptolemy...
上、下省的头主
...lord of the Upper and Lower regions...
太阳神、赫拉斯、托斯、塔…之子
...son of Ra, of Horus and of Thoth, beloved of--
等等…不一而足…欢迎我
Et cetera, et cetera. You welcome me.
我是朱利斯凯撒 罗马元老院执政官麦希马斯
And I, Gaius Julius Caesar, Pontifex Maximus...
…等等，感谢你
...et cetera, et cetera, thank you.
罗马元老院与人民向托勒密国王以及…
From the Senate and people of Rome, hail King Ptolemy.
舆他共治的姊姊克莉奥佩特拉女王致敬
And his sister and co-ruler, Queen Cleopatra?
事实并非如此 克莉奥佩特拉已死！
They won't tell you so, but Cleopatra's dead.
她企图谋杀我 我们将她放逐到沙漠
She tried to kill me, and we chased her into the desert.
她已死在那儿
And there she died.
事实上皇姊…
Whereas it is true that His Majesty's sister...
屡次想谋杀国王
...repeatedly plotted to have him killed...
克莉奥佩特拉已死却非事实
...it is not true that Cleopatra is dead.
她只是逃离了亚历山卓
Whereas it is true that she fled from Alexandria--
抱歉打扰你
I seem to always interrupt you...
但我想问清楚
...but the search for truth can go on and on.
你是波第诺斯？
Pothinus, is it not?
宫廷大臣… 就是托勒密国王的最高宦官了
Lord Chamberlain and chief eunuch to King Ptolemy. An exalted rank.
成就非凡，或者说…牺牲重大
Obtained not without certain, shall we say, sacrifice.
席铎特斯，你说是吗？
Theodotus, am I right?
陛下历史、哲学舆野心的导师
Tutor to His Majesty in history, philosophy and ambition.
亚其勒斯，听说你是个好战士
And Achillas. They say you're a good soldier.
- 克莉奥佩特拉女王在哪里？ - 舆她的军队同在
-As one to another, where is Cleopatra? -With her army.
你有多少军队对付她？
And how many of your men between her and Alexandria?
- 足够的军队 - 我可以说句话吗？
-Enough. -May I speak?
伟大的凯撒心平气和而来
Surely you have come in peace.
我们也热诚、隆重的欢迎你
And we present ourselves to you in warm and respectful welcome.
我们唯一的问题是内政问题
Our only problem being an internal one, of concern only to us...
凯撒为何而来？
...why have you come, Caesar?
托勒密与克莉奥佩特拉之父驾崩时
As we all know, when the father of both Ptolemy and Cleopatra died...
遗诏指示二人共同治理埃及
...he named the two of them to rule jointly over Egypt.
罗马身为保护者与遗诏执行者
Rome was appointed their guardian and the executor of his will.
我代表罗马质疑 何以克莉奥佩特拉被驱逐
I have come in the name of Rome to ask why Cleopatra has been deposed...
我来是解决她与托勒密之争
...to resolve the differences between her and King Ptolemy...
希望他们可以和平共治
...and to see that they peacefully resume their joint rule of Egypt.
恐怕困难重重 克莉奥佩特拉已犯罪失权
That will be difficult. Cleopatra has forfeited her right.
我设法秉公处理
I shall try to decide justly.
你们难道看不出来？ 他要带克莉奥佩特拉回来
Don't you see he'll send for her? He'll bring her back!
或者烈日太过锺情
The sun which sheds its grace upon the ruler of the two lands...
国王陛下
...burns too brightly perhaps.
如果托勒密国王愿意先行回宫…
If Lord Ptolemy wishes to retire--
我绝对没这个意愿
I wish nothing of the kind!
我不会回宫 除非你给他看那个！
I won't be put out of the way until I've watched you give him that!
真对不起，我几乎忘记了
A thousand pardons, I had almost forgotten.
我王托勒密有份礼物 送给凯撒以袁欢迎之诚
Lord Ptolemy wishes to enhance his welcome by a gift of some importance.
感激厚礼相赠
Most generous.
戒指，庞培的戒指给他！
The ring. Give him Pompey's ring.
代表我王对凯撒
And now the token of His Majesty's affection for Rome...
与罗焉的敬意
...and regard for Caesar.
庞培大帝！
Pompey the Great.
他们说死人不会咬人的
Dead men, they say, do not bite.
这礼物你满意吗，凯撒？
Does it please you, Caesar?
他们说这礼物会令你很开心
They said it would please you very much.
烈日果真会灼身
The sun does shed its grace too brightly.
这对王者不利
It has become too hot here for kings.
吾王托勒密要先行告退！
My Lord Ptolemy will retire.
庞培是罗马荣誉的守护者
For His Majesty, a Roman guard of honor.
庞培应该不是你杀的吧？
It was not by your hand, of course.
如果你曾听说过我的事 你会比较了解我
If, as you say, you've been told of me, you know better, Caesar.
请照顾我手下的起居饮食
My men shall be properly housed and fed.
- 我可以说句话吗？ - 有人问你才可发言
-May I speak? -Not until you're spoken to.
我要求住在皇宫里
I'll require rooms in the palace.
本人有幸亲自护驾
I shall consider myself honored to escort you.
除了你，任何人都可以
Anyone but you.
尽全力打探
Find the rest of Pompey.
庞培的尸首
Tear out a thousand tongues, but find him.
为他举行净身
Have him purified...
含银币等尊荣之礼
...the coin in the mouth and the rest, honorably.
当然
Of course.
眼下我们必须据有…
For now, this is what we must hold.
月门和其他三个要点 这、这和这儿
Moon gate and three others. Here, here and here.
我们的部署如何？
How are we placed?
第十军团守月门 其余的都在后备
The 10th slingers on the moon gate. The rest in reserve.
第十二军团分散在其他位置 兵力很少，凯撒
The 12th holding all other positions. Very thin.
目前这样足够了
For now, deep enough.
- 有没有验过井水？ - 有咸味，但可以喝
-Have we tested the wells? -The water's brackish, but drinkable.
他们的玉米和小麦也要注意
So far. Keep an eye on them. Watch the corn and wheat.
为什么？我们供给无虞 大可无限供应
With our supplies secure, we can hold indefinitely.
一星期或许够 但现在时间似乎不够用
For a week, perhaps. For the time being, time enough.
你有什么事？
What do you want?
这人可以信任吗？
Is the man to be trusted?
看来有人要送礼物给我
Seems someone's brought me a gift...
是克莉奥佩特拉女王送的
...from Queen Cleopatra.
地毯小贩
Apparently, a rug peddler.
但弗拉维乌斯不信
Flavius doubts it.
他太了解皇宫了
He seems to know the palace very well.
他经由秘道突然出现 那秘道没有人知道
He appeared through a secret passage which none of the men knew.
波第诺斯可能以 克莉奥佩特拉之名派刺客来
Pothinus might send an assassin in Cleopatra's name.
带他进来
Have the man brought in.
你就是帮克莉奥佩特拉送礼物来的人？
Are you the one who brings a gift from Cleopatra?
把东西放下，立刻离开
Put it down and go.
女王吩咐我亲手送交凯撒
It is the command of my queen I deliver her gift personally.
我是凯撒，将东西放在我面前
I am Caesar. Lay it here before me.
亚格里巴，你不是凯撒
Forgive me, Admiral Agrippa, but you're not Caesar.
鲁非欧将军也不是 朱曼尼卡斯当然也不是
Nor you, General Rufio. Nor you, Germanicus.
女王的礼物只有凯撒…
My queen's gift is for the eyes of Caesar...
可以看
...alone.
- 那地毯看来没什么特别 - 不，凯撒…
-It seems harmless enough. -No, Caesar!
鲁非欧，借剑给我 有东西要割断
You can lend me your sword, Rufio. It may require some cutting.
你搬地毯的方法真奇特
Odd way to carry a rug.
用肩膀抬不是比较轻松吗？
Isn't it easier to sling it over your shoulder?
那样比较不舒服
It was less comfortable that way.
- 你不舒服，还是地毯？ - 凯撒，你的剑…
-For you or the rug? -That sword, Caesar.
地毯手工很精细 我可否为你解下？
The rug is such a delicate weave. If I may untie it for you.
将它反转过来
Turn it over first.
- 地毯已经面向上了 - 我要底向上
-But the rug is right-side up. -I want it the wrong side up.
- 要我用剑来反转吗？ - 不不不！
-Should I flip it over with my sword? -No, no, no.
货物好坏，一看…
I find one can tell more about the quality of merchandise...
背面就知道
...by examining the back side first.
克莉奥佩特拉女王万岁… 王室的荣耀
All hail Cleopatra, kindred of Horus and Ra...
日月的光荣 埃瑟丝女神之女
...beloved of the moon and sun, daughter to Isis...
至高无上的埃及女王
...and of Upper and Lower Egypt, queen.
谢谢
Thank you.
这里
Here.
把这手令交给夜更侍卫队长
Take this to the captain of the night watch.
他会预备好女王的侍卫队
He'll see the queen's quarters are made ready to her.
别动
Stay where you are.
- 我叫你走了吗？ - 没有，陛下
-Have I dismissed you? -No, Your Majesty.
这是我的地方
This is my palace, Caesar.
由我发号拖令
All of it is available to me at my will.
我不是你的犯人 而你是我的客人
I am not your prisoner. If anything, you are my guest.
悉听尊便
Most kind.
至于帮我预备侍卫队…
And as for having my quarters, as you put it, made ready...
我的侍女已将其他人带出
...my chief handmaiden has, by now, brought the others out of hiding.
应该全部出来了
They should almost be finished.
恐怕不可能，外面戒备深严
Impossible. The doors are under guard.
此处有无数的门
There are doors, and doors.
当然
Oh, yes. Of course.
改天带我参观您的皇宫
You must take me on a tour someday within the walls of your palace.
- 你还等什么？ - 等您下令让我离开
-What are you waiting for? -Permission to leave.
可以走了
Granted.
阿波罗德斯
Apollodorus.
谢谢你
Thank you.
很高兴你收到我的召唤 而且能够…
I'm pleased you received my summons and were able to--
召唤？我没有收到
Summons? I'm pleased to say I received nothing of the kind.
要我回应我真的十分讶异
I'm surprised you thought I would answer one.
小姐，你的地毯旅程显然不累
Young lady, the voyage in your non-magic carpet...
但我今天真的很累了
...has apparently not tired you, but I'm exhausted.
凯撒，我们必须互相了解
Caesar, it is essential we understand each other.
只有我能帮你…
Only through me can you hope to escape...
脱离这个危险
...the desperate situation in which you find yourself.
如果是我的话 我决不会吃那个水果
I wouldn't bite into that.
是你带来的吗？ 尝过吗？
Did you bring it with you? Have you had it tasted?
如没有，可能有毒
If neither, it's probably poisoned.
这也是脱离危险的方法之一
At least it's another way out of the desperate situation in which I'm found.
你对我很容忍，不是吗？
You're being tolerant of me, aren't you?
是因为你比我年长很多？
Is it because you're so much older?
你的地图比我的逊色
Your maps are inferior. Out-of-date, compared to mine.
它和我一样都老了
They and I have aged together.
西边的湖泊位置不对
The lakes to the west are poorly marked...
几个重要山丘甚至没标记
...certain important hill positions not even noted.
请你帮我的绘图师舆全体官兵上课
I must arrange for you to address my mapmakers and general staff.
我们一开始就不和
We've gotten off to a bad start, haven't we?
不过是倒顺你的毛
I've rubbed you the wrong way.
小姐，其实你根本不该摸
I'm not sure I want to be rubbed by you at all, young lady.
请问我可否坐下？
It is permissible for me to sit, is it not?
凯撒，请尽快让我单独登上埃及王位
As quickly as possible you must set me alone on the throne of Egypt.
我的任务是平息你们姊弟的纷争
My mission is to put to an end the tiresome squabbling between your brother and you.
你不是个傻瓜吧？
You're not a fool. Or are you?
恕不自谦，应该不是吧
Immodestly, perhaps, no.
你见过我弟弟 听过他说话吧？
You've seen my brother and listened to him?
那数典忘宗邪恶的人
And that truly evil man to whom he belongs?
见过
Yes.
我们都同意罗马一向…
Shall we agree upon what Rome really wants...
对埃及的倚赖吗？
...has always wanted of Egypt?
玉米、谷物和珍宝
Corn, grain, treasure. It's the old story.
一直以来，罗马的伟大 建立在埃及的富足之上
Roman greatness built upon Egyptian riches.
你要和平取得这些物资
You shall have them. You shall have them all and in peace.
办法只得一个
But there is only one way.
让我当女王
My way. Make me queen.
听起来像最后通牒
That sounds very much like an ultimatum.
没有其他方法
There is no other way.
下通牒的人，几分钟前…
For one whose assets, up to a few moments ago...
仅有一个忠仆和一张地毯
...was a devoted slave and a rolled-up carpet....
现在有了你，凯撒
But I have you now, Caesar.
而且我有军队
Besides, there are my armies...
没有一个凡人可以打败我
...and the simple fact that no mortal hand can destroy me.
记得你自称具有神力
Yes, I recall some mention of an obsession...
埃瑟丝女神降世
...you have about your divinity.
对吗？
Isis, is it not?
我警告你小心说话
I shall have to insist that you mind what you say.
我是埃瑟丝女神 受千万人爱戴
I am Isis. I am worshiped by millions who believe it.
不要用罗马将军们的…
Do not confuse what I am...
保护神
...with the so-called divine origin...
混淆我的身分
...that every Roman general acquires together with his shield.
你们不是维纳斯的近亲吗？
It was Venus you chose to be descended from, wasn't it?
容许我表达我小小的固执
I must now do a little insisting of my own.
首先，你始终是旅途困倦 需要休息…
First, your journey has tired you and you wish to retire.
我不是你的仆人 你无权遣我走
I am not your servant, Caesar. Do not dismiss me.
第二，你停发军饷
Secondly, you have no armies, young lady.
你的军队跑光了
They are gone because you could not pay them.
埃及的财富你都无法享用
Egypt's riches are not available for your own use...
更何况是赠与他人
...much less to give away. Perhaps in a day or two...
- 我们改天再谈吧 - 那对我俩…
-...we can speak again. -That may be too late...
都太迟了
...for both of us.
我要负责你的安全
Your safety will be my responsibility.
你自己的安全呢？
And what about your own?
目前，我已有对策
I am prepared, I believe, for the time being.
希望如此吧
I hope so.
希望你像传闻中一样
I hope you are as wise, as brilliant...
明智而杰出，像神一样
...the god they say you are.
罗马将军轻易就被神化
You Roman generals become divine so quickly.
只要几场胜仗和屠杀
A few victories, a few massacres.
昨天庞培还是个神
Only yesterday, Pompey was a god.
- 今天不是惨遭屠杀吗？ - 是的
-They murdered him, didn't they? -Yes.
因为他们以为你会高兴
Because they thought it would please you.
- 你高兴吗？ - 不
-It didn't, did it? -No.
今天，我想起我女儿很喜欢他
Today I found myself remembering how much my daughter loved him.
她因为想为他生子而丧命
She died trying to bear him a son.
她给他这个戒指
She gave him this ring.
好好睡一觉
Sleep well tonight, Caesar.
未来几天可不好过啊
These next days may be difficult for you.
晚安
Good night.
朱曼尼卡斯 派个侍卫送女王回府
Germanicus, a guard to escort Queen Cleopatra to her apartments.
侍卫！
Guards!
走廊很暗，各位
The corridors are dark, gentlemen.
但不必怕，有我在这里
But you mustn't be afraid. I am with you.
今晚任务是否完成了？
Haven't we covered everything we can tonight, sir?
- 是的，其他留待明天 - 不，还有几件事
-Perhaps a fresh start in the morning. -No, a few more matters.
例如，你不觉得我们的地图…
Rufio, has it occurred to you that our maps of this area...
有点不妥吗？
...are not quite what they should be?
不会啊，你怎会这样想？
Why, no. What makes you think they're not?
对这种事我有直觉
I have an instinct about these things.
根据资料是马其顿血统
--actually of Macedonian descent.
没有埃及血缘
No officially-admitted Egyptian blood.
克莉奥佩特拉以足智多谋
"Reputed to be extremely intelligent and sharp of wit.
阅历丰富著称 擅长科学…
Queen Cleopatra is widely read. Well-versed in the sciences...
与算术
...and mathematics.
并精通七国语言
She speaks seven languages proficiently.
若非身为女人她会是知识份子
Were she not a woman, she'd be considered an intellectual."
但我发现知识份子最无趣
Nothing bores me so much as an intellectual.
所以你是个好舰队司令 亚格里巴
Makes a better admiral of you, Agrippa.
这份文件 海军会比较有兴趣
Here's something of more interest to the navy:
为达到目的克莉奥佩特拉 利用刑罚、毒药…
"In obtaining her objectives, she has been known to use torture, poison...
甚至她娇人的性吸引力
...and even her own sexual talents, which are said to be considerable.
听说她的爱人多不胜数 也就是说名字多得说不完
Her lovers, I am told, are listed more easily by number than by name.
她对男人很主动
It is said that she chooses in the manner of a man...
并非被动等待
...rather than wait to be chosen after womanly fashion."
所以我们才不让…
Well, there's more reason than we thought...
你们单独相处
...for not wanting to leave you two alone, eh, sir?
抱歉，鲁非欧，我没听见
I'm sorry, I wasn't listening.
你信得过克莉奥佩特拉？
Are you inclined to trust Cleopatra?
信任？门都没有
Trust? Not for a minute.
我对信任一词一向定义模糊
"Trust." The word has always made me apprehensive.
就像酒，后劲教我难以消受
Like wine, whenever I've tried it, the aftereffects have not been good.
所以我不喝酒…
So I've given up wine...
也不信任他人
...and trusting.
各位，今天很累了
Oh, it's been a long and difficult day, gentlemen.
往后几天或会更累
The next few may be even longer and more difficult.
- 晚安 - 晚安
-Good night. -Good night.
弗拉维乌斯！
Flavius!
秋天又来了，心爱的莱比雅
It is autumn again, my best-loved Lesbia
看，树叶不停的飘落…飘落
Look, the torrents of Roman leaves Are falling, falling
跟着，爱人们在春之吻中苏醒
And lovers revive in kisses The promise of spring
夜莺叫声中寒冬将远去…
Which will end the winter world With new nightingales calling
我先试你的食物
I taste your food, daughter of Isis...
有毒就毒我好了
...and if there be harm in it, let the harm fall upon me.
爱终将有凋萎的一天
But love must bring Despair one day
当美丽与哀愁…
As beauty, sorrow
- 为什么停下来？费比斯？ - 走廊外有骚动
-Why do you stop, Phoebus? -In the corridor, there is movement.
罗马人用象般的脚踩地
That's how the Romans frighten the enemy...
- 希望可以吓退敌人 - 不，有个人
-...by stamping their elephant feet. -No, this is one man...
后面有一班人跟着
...followed by others.
- 应该是凯撒 - 是吗？
-Caesar, I would say. -Would you?
不能让凯撒失望
We must not disappoint the mighty Caesar.
罗马人对我的沐浴
The Romans tell fabulous tales of my bath...
女仆…
...and handmaidens...
和道德观充满了幻想
...and my morals.
克莉奥佩特拉邀我作伴
Cleopatra's requested an audience with me.
- 那是昨天的事，凯撒 - 我有重要的事
-That was yesterday, Caesar. -I've been occupied.
女王正在沐浴 凯撒能否稍后
The queen is occupied with her bath. Perhaps Caesar could return later...
- 或明天再来？ - 恐怕不能捉住他
-...or tomorrow. -I'm afraid not. Hold him.
不，不要伤害他
No, don't hurt him.
你是个好人，阿波罗德斯
You're a good man, Apollodorus.
希望你能明白
I hope you're appreciated.
在这里等我
Wait here for me.
既然如此，让我们活下去并且相爱 不要理会什么
Ah, then let us live and love Without one thought
处女年华老去的闲话
For the gossip of virgins Now grown old and stale
太阳下山后依旧会升起
Suns go down and may return
但希望之光若熄灭
But once put out Our own brief light
将是无尽的长眠
We sleep through One eternal night
有人闯入！一个男人
An intruder! A man!
原来是你
Oh, it's you.
你想见我？
You wanted to see me?
我昨天召你
I summoned you yesterday...
来王宫见我
...to an audience in my throne room.
但未获准到那里
I was told I was not permitted to go there.
太靠近你弟弟的指挥中心 以及他的手下
It's too close to the quarters occupied by your brother and the rest.
我爱到哪儿就到哪儿！
I will not be told where I can go and where I cannot go!
显然你并不需要我
Since there's nothing you want....
除了王位！
Except my throne!
至少你盛装前来
At least you've dressed properly for my presence.
穿了最好的盔甲？
Your best armor?
也许是吧，但不是因为尊重你
Almost, but I'm afraid it's not being worn in your honor.
我知道
I know.
今早你去拜祭亚历山大的坟
This morning, you paid a formal visit to the tomb of Alexander.
独自凭吊石棺很久…
You remained alone beside the sarcophagus for some time.
我倒想知道你怎会知道
I'd like to know how you know.
低头凝视
Just staring down at him.
还流下眼泪
And then you cried.
凯撒，你为何流泪？
Why did you cry, Caesar?
他朗诵的很好
That man recites beautifully.
- 他是盲人吗？ - 不要伤害他
-Is he blind? -Don't you hurt him.
我不会伤害将卡图卢斯 朗诵得这么好的人
I won't. Not anyone who speaks Catullus so well.
卡图卢斯不赞同你怎么不杀他？
Catullus doesn't approve of you. Why haven't you had him killed?
因为我赞同他
Because I approve of him.
我无意取悦你，凯撒
My desire to please you, Caesar Is very slight
更不管你是黑人或白人
Nor do I greatly care to know If you are black or white
亚其勒斯在部署全军 开往亚历山卓
Achillas is moving his entire army to Alexandria.
今晚，他的兵力将会是你的二三十倍
By tonight, he'll outnumber you 20-to-1 , 30-to-1 .
他会将皇家禁地重重包围
He'll have the royal enclosure entirely surrounded.
除了靠海这一边
Except to the sea.
你打算出海逃走，凯撒？
Do you plan to sail away, great Caesar?
目前没这个打算
Not for the time being.
亚其勒斯明后天开始攻击
Achillas may attack tomorrow, the next day...
- 只等他下决定！ - 非常可能
-...whenever it suits him! -Very probable.
凯撒，即使是做梦…
In your wildest dreams, Caesar, how can you possibly hope to hold...
你怎可能以寡敌众？
...the gates of this enclosure against such odds?
看你还怎么说目前！
And if you say once more, "For the time being"....
我的军官说短则一周 长则无尽期
My officers say anything from a week to indefinitely.
你估计呢？
What would you estimate?
你是说缺水
Before you're without water...
断粮
...without food...
还是全军覆没？ 一个接一个在屋顶被杀
...your troops slaughtered, picked off from the rooftops...
在妓院中毒身亡
...poisoned in the brothels?
几天吧，凯撒，最多几天
A few days, Caesar. At the most, a few days.
我相当同意
I'm inclined to agree with you.
知不知道卡图卢斯有首诗？
Young man, do you know this of Catullus?
给我千个吻
Give me a thousand And a thousand kisses
再多就数不清了
When we have many thousand more We'll scramble them
忘记数字
And forget the score
忌妒怎会自知
So evil envy will not know How high the count
忌妒的深度
And cast its evil eye
即使在皇室也没有如此愉快
It couldn't have been as pleasant in the throne room.
我无意取悦你，凯撒…
"My desire to please you, Caesar, Is very slight--"
不要动
Be still!
凯撒，我有句话… 非常重要
Caesar, a word. It's important.
埃及船只停靠西港 装载人员和武器
The Egyptian galleys in the harbor have been taking on men and armaments.
- 何时将对我们动手？ - 明日清早
-When will they be prepared? -Tomorrow, with the morning wind.
今晚将他们烧了
Burn them tonight.
船只紧靠岸边
Their ships lie close to shore.
- 火势可能蔓延到城里 - 希望是不会
-The fire may spread to the city. -Let's hope it doesn't.
但不能冒被封锁的危险
I can't risk a blockade.
记住，今晚之前不要动手秘密做准备
Remember, not before tonight. Prepare as secretly as possible.
我需要今天
I need this day.
祝你好运
Good luck.
为何不可以在今晚之前动手？ 为何凯撒需要今天？
Why not before tonight, my lord? Why does Caesar need this day?
目前，天机不可泄漏
I can't give you that information, for the time being.
弗拉维乌斯
Flavius.
凯撒，在这儿，刚到
Here it is, Caesar. Just arrived.
神真会作弄我们，鲁非欧
The gods shouldn't tantalize us so, Rufio.
比我希望的还好
It's even better than I’d hoped.
- 快走，时间不多 - 凯撒万岁
-Be on your way, you haven't much time. -Hail Caesar.
这称为癫痫症因为肌肉抽搐
It's called an epilepse because of the arching caused by muscular spasms...
引起剧痛 古希腊人认为
...the contortions. The early Greeks considered...
患者因而得神明偏爱
...those who suffered from it to be favored by the gods.
据说亚历山大帝
The great Alexander, they say...
有此癫痫症
...had this falling sickness.
听说凯撒也有
And, so they say, the mighty Caesar too.
陛下恕罪，西索吉诺斯图书馆！
Your Majesty, forgive me. Sosigenes, the library.
- 说清楚 - 罗马人放火
-What are you saying? -The Romans set fire...
- 烧埃及船舰！ - 是时候了
-...to the Egyptian fleet. -It's about time.
你看，火势蔓延到城里了！
Come see for yourself. The fire's spread to the city.
烧着几栋房子
-The city? -Just a few buildings...
图书馆着火了
...but the library is burning.
大图书馆…
The great library.
亚里士多德的手稿…
Aristotle's manuscripts.
柏拉图的评论、剧本、史料…
The Platonic commentaries, the plays, the histories.
希伯来神明的圣经！
The Testament of the Hebrew god.
珍贵的书籍！
The Book of Books.
风将火势吹向商船 至少有四、五艘被烧掉
-Wind blew into the merchant shipping. -Four or five burned and sank right here.
- 我们的船只呢？ - 安全无事
-And our ships? -Safe and dry.
但囚犯们包围住 我需要帮手
Prisoners are surrendering in droves. I need help.
- 没人手，马上还需要水手帮忙 - 站住！
-Not one man. I may need your sailors. -Halt!
不要将我的武器拿走！
Take your hands off me!
你该常常来袭击我的侍卫 打仗似乎使你更为美艳
You should attack my guards more often. Battle seems to become you.
你变得愈来愈美丽
You grow more beautiful each time I see you.
而你的头愈来愈秃！
And you grow bolder.
愈来愈忙
And busier.
- 此刻的确非常忙，恕不奉陪 - 有没有闻到烟味？
-Actually, we're extremely busy-- -Do you smell smoke?
我们必须烧毁埃及舰队
We found it necessary to burn the Egyptian fleet.
船原本在水上
The ships were in the water.
有必要烧街道吗？
Did you find it necessary to burn them in the streets?
几只商船着火
Merchant ships caught fire.
桅杆塌向街上的屋
The burning masts fell. Some houses--
其中之一是亚历山卓的大图书馆
One of them, the great Library of Alexandria.
听说了，非常抱歉
Yes, I’ve been told. I'm extremely sorry.
- 若不介意，我不得不请你… - 我很介意
-Now, if you don't mind, I must ask-- -I do mind.
你要不要将火扑灭？
Are you putting the fire out?
我们正在把埃及囚犯组成消防队
We're forming prisoners into fire brigades.
难道罗马人只懂放火？
Oh, I see. Romans only start fires, is that it?
小孩不要来烦大人
Have you broken out of your nursery to come irritate the adults?
改天吧，现在很忙！
Another time, we're working.
- 要不要将她赶走，凯撒？ - 用罗马人的天赋搞破坏！
-Shall we remove her for you, Caesar? -Use that Roman genius for destruction.
把金字塔拆了，城市也夷平！
Tear down pyramids, wipe out cities!
你们这些野蛮人竟然烧图书馆
How dare you and the rest of your barbarians set fire to my library?
大玩征服者游戏，伟大的凯撒
Play conqueror all you want, mighty Caesar.
尽管烧杀掳掠千万人…
Rape, murder, pillage thousands, millions of human beings.
但你们这些野蛮人…
But neither you nor any other barbarian...
无权摧毁人类文明！
...has the right to destroy one human thought!
够了！让我单独跟她谈谈
Enough! Leave me alone with her.
很快就会结束，到时我会通知你
I will send for you when I finish. It won't be long.
剑？标枪？
Swords? Javelins?
还是放火？
Or are you going to set me on fire?
该是我们互相了解的时候了
The time has come for us to understand each other.
不管你怎样说，我就是凯撒
Whatever else I may be, in your opinion, first of all, I am Caesar.
而我是克莉奥佩特拉 埃瑟丝女神之女！
And I am Cleopatra, queen, daughter of Isis!
我说你是什么…
If I say so and when I say so, you are what I say you are...
你就是什么！
...nothing more.
凯撒万岁
Hail Caesar!
你，多代近亲通婚所生的白痴
You, descendant of inbred generations of incestuous mental defectives...
- 竟敢叫我们野蛮人！ - 野蛮人！
-...how dare you call anyone barbarian. -Barbarian!
你的先人是只会吹笛子的醉酒佬 一路靠贿赂登上王位
Daughter of a drunkard who bribed his way to the throne.
- 你一将功成万骨枯，记得吗？ - 我受够了你的装腔作势
-Your price was too high, remember? -I've had my fill with you pretenders...
- 脚下尽是光荣的废墟 - 我在意的是未来
-...parading on ruins of your past glories. -Only the future concerns me.
- 既然如此，照我的话去做 - 照你的话去做？
-Keep out of my affairs, do as I say. -Do as you say?
真的吗？
Literally?
就像你已征服了我？
As if I were something you had conquered?
只要我如此认为
If I choose to regard you as such.
我是不是该乖乖跟你合作…
Am I to understand that you're free to do with me whatever you want...
你可以为所欲为？
...whenever you want?
是的，这见解十分正确
Yes, I want that understood.
你干脆戴上皇冠…
Won't you at least wear your laurel wreath...
我清楚记得是蒙凯撒宠幸？
...so I can be reminded it's the divine Caesar that honors me so?
你讲得太多了
You talk too much.
我这样子
I promise you...
你不会喜欢的
...you won't like me this way.
凯撒！月门受到袭击！
Caesar! An attack on the moon gate!
月门！武力袭击！
The moon gate. An attack in force!
炮塔必需摧毁
Those ballistas need eliminating.
派出战龟
Send out a turtle.
备妥战龟！
Form the turtle!
该是进攻的好时机
Now is the time for us to attack!
- 不 - 但是我们已用了预备军
-No. -We have a full legion in reserve.
守在这里就可以了
We hold our positions here.
离黎明两小时守住这里就可以了
Two hours till dawn. We'll hold where we are.
- 天亮之后呢？ - 你知道的
-And what happens at dawn? -I thought you knew.
太阳升起来啊
The sun comes up.
告诉部下我们已取得胜利
Tell the men they've won.
犒赏守门有功的士卫
Liberty and wine for defenders of the gate.
所有后备兵力移至亚其勒背后
All reserves, cavalry, every man available, move out behind Achillas.
- 两面包抄 - 包抄的另一边呢？
-We have him in a vise. -What is the other half of this vise?
鲁非欧和密斯里达的部队
Rufio and the armies of Mithradates. He left last night to meet them.
密斯里达？他怎会那么快？
Mithradates? How could he get here this fast?
我们出航埃及时他已出发
I sent him when we sailed for Egypt.
任何有理智的将军 都不会妄想靠两队军队拿下亚历山卓
No general in his right mind can hold Alexandria with two legions...
你们不是常常那么说吗？
...as you and others have repeatedly pointed out to me.
我尝你的酒，埃瑟丝女神之女
I taste your drink, daughter of Isis...
若有毒，就毒死我吧
...and if there be harm in it, let the harm fall upon me.
洛托斯！
Lotus.
喝过之后将杯边擦干净 知道为什么吗？
You wiped the rim of the cup after you tasted it. Why?
- 为什么？ - 以免被我的咀污染
Why? So my mouth would not soil it.
洛托斯
Lotus...
再尝一口
...taste it again.
波第洛斯说要杀我！ 原谅我
Pothinus said he would have me killed. Forgive me, Majesty.
陛下，原谅我！
Forgive me. Forgive me.
我原谅你
I forgive you.
现在喝吧
Now drink it.
阿波罗德斯！
Apollodorus!
欢迎罗马元老院执政官
Great silence for Gaius Julius Caesar...
朱利斯凯撒
...consul of the senate of the people of Rome.
全体肃立
You will all stand.
以下所讲的
Let what is said be recorded...
是代表罗马元老院之审判与裁定
...as the judgment and decree of the Senate and people of Rome.
没有审判啊
There is no judgment here.
裁定也按克莉奥佩特拉的意思
And the decree not Rome's, but Cleopatra's.
你被她骗了，凯撒
She has lied to you, Caesar.
她跟她的奴仆骗了你！
She and her slaves lie to you.
尚未请你离席，波第诺斯
You have not been accused, Pothinus. Thus far.
兹控告你煽动对罗马之战
You are now charged with inciting and abetting war against the Roman army.
以及图谋暗杀克莉奥佩特拉
You are now charged with plotting to assassinate Queen Cleopatra.
两项罪名成立，宣判死刑
You are guilty of both. You are sentenced to death.
太光了，遮掉一些光线？
It's too bright in here. Shut out some of the sun.
凯撒，连你也想杀我
Are you going to kill me too, Caesar?
我的罪名是什么？
What am I accused of?
托勒密国王不再受罗马保护
King Ptolemy is hereby removed from the protective custody of Rome.
立刻送返
He'll leave within the hour...
亚其勒斯将军的营中
...and be conducted safely to the camp of Achillas.
送我回我的部队？
Achillas! You're going to send me back to my own troops?
他的军师席铎特斯亦将会同行
He is to be accompanied by his learned tutor, Theodotus.
听到没有？你也获救了！
Do you hear that? You'll be saved along with me.
不要这么开心，小白痴！
Stop grinning, you little idiot.
恕我多口讲句 你明知亚其勒斯被包抄夹在…
May I speak? You know that Achillas is trapped...
密斯里达和你的部队之中
...between your own legions and the armies of Mithradates.
将我王送去等于送死
To send His Majesty to fight them may mean his death.
此乃身为刖的风险
An occupational hazard for those who will be king.
等等
But then certainly not I, Caesar.
但我不是一国之君 也不是将领，不懂战争
I'm no king, nor general. What do I know of war?
只是个学者
A simple scholar.
只是个史弱书生
A man of thoughts and words.
不用多言！
Too many words. Enough.
一切按宣判执行
Let all be done properly as decreed.
弗拉维乌斯
Flavius.
将匕首还给阿波罗德斯
Find Apollodorus. Return his dagger to him.
先洗干净 上面沾满波第诺斯的血
You might clean it first. It has Pothinus all over it.
好，好，我知道我累了 我会去睡
Yes, yes, I know I'm tired. I promise I'll sleep.
你…啊 对不起，差点伤到你
You have my apologies for what almost happened to you.
凯撒，可以说几句话吗？
Caesar, will you talk with me for just a minute?
昨天很忙，昨晚没空
Yesterday was full. Tonight was long.
今早事情又多
This morning has not been uneventful.
你事前知不知道
Did you know that Apollodorus would kill Pothinus?
阿波罗德斯要杀波第诺斯？ 他很耐心的等到宣判死刑
He was kind enough to wait until Rome had passed sentence of death.
我弟弟
And my brother...
和席铎特斯
...and Theodotus?
也可能被杀
They too will be killed, possibly.
可能吧
Probably.
陛下抱歉，我真的很累了
Your Majesty, I’m truly weary.
你早知道没有真正的危险
You knew all along, didn't you, that there was no real danger.
密斯里达正在赶来
That Mithradates was on his way to reinforce you.
你为什么不告诉我？
Why didn't you tell me?
我说我有备而来你不相信
I said I was prepared. You wouldn't believe me.
- 不是我无礼，我真的要… - 我本来会信任你
-I really must insist-- -I would've believed you.
- 是你不信任我吧？ - 当然不是！
-You didn't trust me. -Not for an instant.
但，刚才
And yet, in these last few minutes...
你确立了我的王位
...you have made me undisputed queen.
成为埃及唯一的统治者为什么？
The sole ruler of Egypt. Why?
明天或晚一点，我们可以谈谈
Perhaps tomorrow, later in the day, we could talk.
- 为什么，凯撒？ - 这最符合罗马的利益，拜托…
-Why, Caesar? -It was best for Rome. Please.
- 最符合埃及的利益 - 也对
-Best for Egypt. -For Egypt too.
克莉奥佩特拉，请你出去！
Cleopatra, get out. I beg of you, get out.
我不需要那个
That will not be needed.
我不需要隐瞒
It wasn't necessary for me to betray myself.
本来我可以叫弗拉维乌斯
I could have called out for Flavius.
你在墙上开了多少个洞窥看？
How many new spy-holes have you dug in the walls?
现在我们也被偷窥？
Are we being watched even now?
看到弗拉维乌斯，叫他进来
If you see Flavius, you might send him to me.
- 还想打发我走？ - 你到底还想要什么？
-Still trying to dismiss me? -What is it you want?
只想帮你
-What more do you want? -To be of help to you.
从来都不会有任何帮助
There never has been help. There never will be.
现在有了
Now there is.
有一天我再也躲不了
One day it'll happen where I cannot hide.
在世人面前…
Where the world will see me fall.
当众倒下
I shall tumble down before the mob...
口吐白沫受人讪笑
...and foam at the mouth and make them laugh.
被暴民撕成碎片
And they'll tear me to pieces.
神也免不了这种疾病
The gods themselves had your sickness.
汉尼拔…甚至亚历山大帝
Hannibal, even the great Alexander.
最终还是倒下
And in the end, they fell.
被暴民撕成碎片
Were torn to pieces by the mob.
你不会
Not you.
我会医好你的
I will see to that.
我以罗马元老院和人民之名… 并依他们的意愿…
In the name of the Senate and the people of Rome and by their will.
埃瑟丝女神宁可放弃她的地位 换取你的美貌
Isis herself would surrender her place in heaven to be as beautiful as you.
你不该看我，任何人都不准
You're not supposed to look at me. No one is.
他们不看，就不知道我看你
If they aren't looking, how do they know I am?
你该跪下
You should be kneeling.
对着这么多到来探访的国王…
Would that do before all these visiting kings?
装作他们都看不见我们？
Making believe they're not watching us?
你的膝盖全是骨头
You have such bony knees.
不只多骨，也不惯做这种事
Not only bony, but unaccustomed to this sort of thing.
如果我们明天一早出发…
If we're to get an early start in the morning--
明天有什么事？
What will it be tomorrow?
更多小麦？
More wheat?
我见到的已比全罗马还要多
What I’ve seen already could feed more legions than Rome ever had.
足以喂饱全世界
There's enough to feed the world.
黄金更多
More gold then.
何不将全世界买下？ 相信你有足够的财力
Why not buy the world? Surely you have enough.
至少能比罗马养更多军队
At least enough to pay more legions than even Rome has ever had.
更多花岗岩、大理石
More granite, more marble...
奴隶爱建什么便建什么
...more millions of slaves to build whatever needs building.
通印度的新路，往东方的捷径
Better routes to India, shorter routes to the East.
埃及无所不有
What can there be in Egypt that I haven't seen?
埃及正因此而成为埃及
Egypt itself. The reason for Egypt.
我的责任在罗马
My responsibility is Rome.
亚历山大明白
Alexander understood it...
可以由埃及统治全世界
...that from Egypt he could rule the world.
他很年轻，你更年轻
He was very young. And you, even younger.
这个年纪的梦全随时间淡去
At your age, such dreams have a reality which grows less in time.
凯撒不再造梦了吗？
Caesar no longer dreams?
对我的身分来说很危险
Dangerous to a man of my calling.
我认为有必要
Necessary, I would have thought.
我不能离开罗马太久 那会有问题
I can't stay away from Rome too long. There are problems.
马克安东尼一直催我回去
Messages from Marc Antony endlessly demanding my return.
回程中，东、北两面还有战争
And on my way back, wars to be fought in the east and north.
即使在罗马也有人作对
Even in Rome itself I'm not without opposition.
用对付亚其勒斯的方法应付
Do to them what you did to Achillas.
性质不同
This is opposition of a different sort.
像蜘蛛网般精巧
They weave it cleverly, lightly, like a cobweb.
蜘蛛网要经常清除
You know what happens when cobwebs are not regularly swept away.
你信任马克安东尼？
Do you trust this Marc Antony?
世上我只有安东尼一个可以信任
If anyone in the world, I trust Antony.
让他扫蜘蛛网，你留在我身边
Let him brush away the cobwebs for you and stay with me.
你宣布了独裁一年
You've been declared dictator for a year.
在这段时间内可以任意行事
You can do what you want with your time.
除了继续独裁，其他什么都可以
Everything but make it stand still.
回罗马途中
If-- When you return to Rome...
要打的仗很重要吗？
...these wars that have to be fought on the way, are they important?
没有一场战争是不重要的
Well, there's no such thing as an unimportant war.
我读过你对高卢战役的评论
I've been reading in your commentaries about your campaigns in Gaul.
我的文笔像不像卡图卢斯？
How does my writing compare with Catullus?
这个嘛…不一样的东西
Well, it's different.
乏味
Dull.
或许描绘得太仔细了
Perhaps a little too much description.
你的话很圆滑 我的评论员布鲁特斯说…
You're being tactful. Some of my critics, Brutus, for one...
我的拉丁文造诣很差
...tell me my Latin is not only ungrammatical, but common.
你放过他不只一次
You spared his life more than once.
听说布鲁特斯是你儿子
People say it's because Brutus is your son.
真的吗？
Is that true?
我没有儿子
I have no son.
- 卡普妮雅，你的第三任妻子 - 第四任
-Calpurnia, your third wife... -Fourth.
结婚多久了？十二年？
...married to you how long? 12 years?
而凯撒仍没有继承人
And still, Caesar has no son, no child at all.
大家都知道卡普妮雅不孕
It is well-known that Calpurnia is barren.
不孕的女人
A woman who cannot bear children...
如同干涸的河流
...is like a river that is dry.
讨论这话题没有意义
I see no purpose in discussing the subject further.
女人负有使枯木结果的责任
A woman, too, must make the barren land fruitful.
使荒地生气蓬勃
She must make life grow where there was no life.
就像尼罗河滋养大地
Just as the Mother Nile feeds and replenishes the earth.
我就是尼罗河
I am the Nile.
我将会有众多子孙
I will bear many sons.
埃瑟丝女神告诉我的
Isis has told me.
我的乳房精于孕育爱与生命
My breasts are filled with love and life.
双臀曲线分明而浑圆
My hips are rounded and well apart.
据说这种女人
Such women, they say...
擅于生儿育女
...have sons.
当你第一次独自站在这里时
That first time when you stood here alone...
为什么流泪？告诉我
...why did you cry? Will you tell me now?
因为我失去了某些东西
Because I had lost something.
- 是什么？ - 我一生的
-What? -A lifetime.
- 时间 - 胡说
-Mine. -Nonsense.
为征服世界，他死时仅三十二岁
Having conquered the world, he died at 32.
我已经五十二岁
I am 52.
我余下的责任是不让人征服
My remaining ambition is to keep the world from conquering me.
你的野心就是他的
Your ambitions must always have been his.
一向如此
They still must be.
三十二岁时在西班牙
Shall I tell you something? When I was 32 in Spain...
见到他的雕像
...I came upon a statue of Alexander.
我也落泪
I wept then too.
即使是当时…
Even then.
我希望你将他的剑带回去
I want you to have his sword to take back with you.
- 埋得太深了 - 挖得出来
-Too deeply embedded. -It can be removed.
埋藏得太久了
It's buried in time.
- 亚历山大的衣钵… - 对凯撒来说太沉重了
-And Alexander's mantle? -Too heavy for Caesar.
他的梦想
His dream then.
凯撒，继承他的梦想
Make his dream yours, Caesar.
他伟大的计划
His grand design.
继续完成它
Pick it up where he left off.
完成他的征服大业
Out of the patchwork of conquests...
统一全世界
...one world.
世界上只有一个国家 地球上只有一个民族
And out of one world, one nation.
和平的过生活
One people on earth living in peace.
你终于说出对我的期望
So you have told me at last what it is you want of me.
亦是我们所想的！
Of us!
这个单一民族 全世界的首都是…
At the center, the capital of this world, one people, one nation...
亚历山卓？
...Alexandria?
- 它是被拣选的 - 但我是罗马人
-He chose it. -I am Roman.
他是希腊人，无关紧要 既然我们是同一民族
He was Greek! What will it matter when we're all one people?
我五十二岁了！他三十二岁时失败！
I am 52. He was 32 and failed.
我们会成功！
We will succeed.
你的梦想，你的野心！
Your dreams, your ambitions.
一辈子不足以实现这个梦想和野心
One lifetime is not enough for such dreams, such ambitions.
亚历山大的衣钵
The cloak of Alexander cannot be too heavy...
埃及舆罗马合力就不会太沉重
...for Rome and Egypt to carry together.
若他的剑埋得太深呢？
And what if his sword is too deeply embedded?
你的剑可以取代它，凯撒！
Yours will replace it, Caesar.
你将政治与热情混淆了
You have a way of mixing politics and passion.
不知何时开始如何终结
Where does one begin and the other leave off?
对我，没有开始，也没有终结
That did not start, nor will it end with me.
不管命运如何
Cleopatra, whatever it is, however it comes out...
总是我自已的命运
...leave me my destiny.
你的命运不再只是你的
Your destiny is no longer just yours.
它也是我的
It's mine too.
很快就会有人 不但继承亚历山大的农钵…
Soon, there will be someone to carry both the cloak of Alexander...
也延续凯撒的权力…
...and the sword of Caesar...
与名声
...and the name of Caesar.
他将以这个身分统治埃及…
And in that name he will rule Egypt.
或世界给予他的任何地方！
And whatever part or all of the world that we give him...
我们的孩子
...our child...
将是你的继承人凯撒！
...will be a son for you, Caesar.
我以埃瑟丝女神之名立誓
By Isis, I swear it.
你可否迟些少回罗马？
Could you put off your return to Rome...
不用太久的
...just long enough?
我已尽快赶来
I came as quickly as I could.
凯撒之家随时欢迎安东尼
Antony is welcome to Caesar's house as often and as quickly as he likes.
身为凯撒的妻子希望你能…
As Caesar's wife, before truth is distorted into vicious gossip...
在谣言散播前知道 你丈夫已娶克莉奥佩特拉
-...I wanted you to hear-- -That my husband has married Cleopatra.
这里有你最喜爱的新酒
There's some fresh wine. One of your many favorites.
据闻婚礼依照埃及宗教礼俗举行
The ceremony, according to vicious gossip, was in the Egyptian religion.
即使如此也不能当真
Even if true, that can't be taken seriously.
婚礼中，他被正式宣布成为埃及的神
During which he was formally declared an Egyptian god.
终于成为神
Officially divine, at last.
凯撒一定很高兴
That must have pleased Caesar.
卡普妮雅我们大家都了解凯撒
Calpurnia, we know Caesar, you and I.
这所谓的婚姻根据罗马法律并无效
This so-called marriage has no validity under Roman law.
一定有某种政治目的
There must be political purpose to it.
或许是罗马与埃及结盟的象征
Perhaps a symbolic ceremony to ratify Rome's alliance with Egypt.
或许只是沉溺于某种野蛮民族的习俗
Perhaps merely indulging some barbaric custom.
尽管既忠诚又体贴
You've been loyal and kind.
也于第一时间赶来
You came as quickly as you could.
但恶意的诺言
Unhappily, vicious gossip travels even faster than you...
比你与真相还快
...and the truth.
你有否听闻克莉奥佩特拉 已怀了凯撒的孩子？
Have you heard, for instance, that Cleopatra is carrying Caesar's child?
没错，安东尼
Yes, Antony.
我们大家…
We know him...
都了解凯撒
...you and I.
未来的罗马
There shall be--
There shall be...
将会是…
...Rome.
强大、孤单而缺乏爱
Mighty and alone and unloved.
女强人
A mistress.
一个女强人会抚养你成人
A mistress shall raise thee again from earth to heaven...
世界将进入公正与爱的时代
...and all the world shall know a golden age of justice and of love.
埃瑟丝女神将有嫡子！
A son shall be born to Isis!
罗马将视他为王
Rome shall know him in cloth of gold.
东方将见他身披圣袍
The East shall see him laden with jewels and treasure.
埃及与罗马之子
A son of Egypt and of Rome!
他将在此面对他的命运！
Here shall he find his destiny!
遵照我的话去做
Do exactly as I tell you.
孩子降世
When the child is born...
涂油宣布为王子后
...after he is anointed and named royal prince...
直接把他带去给凯撒
...take him to Caesar.
带凯撒来…
Bring Caesar here.
不！ 照我的说话
No. Exactly as I tell you.
将孩子带给凯撒 当着他手下面前
Take the child to Caesar, in front of his men.
明白吗？
Do you understand?
当着罗马人面前
In front of all the Romans.
将孩子放在凯撒面前
Lay him at Caesar's feet.
凯撒面前
At Caesar's feet.
我会照你的吩咐去做
I will do just as you say.
不用怕，王者出生从未试过有任何差错
Fear not. We have never lost a Caesar.
完全是荒诞无稽之谈
That remark was insubordinate and in bad taste!
凯撒，罗马法律规条中
Caesar, remember Roman law.
一旦当众抱起婴孩…
If you pick up this child you acknowledge it's yours...
他将被视为罗马人及你的继承人
...and a citizen of Rome, as your heir.
一个男孩！
A son.
我有儿子了！
I have a son!
- 凯撒万岁！ - 凯撒万岁！
-Hail Caesar! -Hail Caesar!
他已被封为埃及国王
He's been made king of Egypt.
他们为他改名为凯撒里奥
They have named their bastard Caesarion.
凯撒里奥王子
Prince Caesarion.
罗马王位继承人的好名字！
What better name for the heir to the throne of Rome.
罗马没有王位
There is no throne of Rome.
凯撒不允许帝制
Nor shall there be, nor would Caesar tolerate one.
儿子
But a son!
我真替凯撒高兴 他一直想要个儿子
We know how much he's wanted one. I am happy for Caesar.
你的高兴很容易理解
Your happiness is understandable enough.
凯撒公开宣称有了儿手
Now that Caesar has publicly recognized a son...
世人不再揣测布鲁特斯的身世
...one need no longer wonder about Brutus.
卡斯卡，若你的身分没人怀疑 是解除痛苦吗？
Is it a relief not to be wondered about, Casca?
公开的身为…
To be known openly as you are for what you are:
骗子、莽汉与懦夫
Liar, swindler, bully and coward.
布鲁特斯，你的话会使卡斯卡掉头而去
Brutus, you'll turn Casca's head with your flattery.
一旦掉头的话他将投入 马克安东尼的阵营
And Casca's head, if turned, will see Marc Antony.
他比凯撒的幼子还可怕
A part of Caesar more to be feared than his infant son.
凯撒逗留埃及这样久 是为罗马着想
But it is for the good of Rome that Caesar has stayed so long in Egypt.
不在罗马，人们视他为神
In his absence, the people have come to worship him as a god.
何必回来跟大家一样做个凡人？
Why should he return to show himself as mortal as the rest?
有些人害怕凯撒的野心
There are those who fear Caesar's ambition.
害怕他摧毁共和政体吗？
But what is there to fear? That he will destroy the republic?
是的，他会
Yes, he will.
他一定会
I promise you he will.
西塞罗，你的舌头虽老却依然锐利
Your tongue is old but sharp, Cicero.
小心它割下自己的脑袋
Be careful how you waggle it. It may cut off your head.
我比较担心你的剑，安东尼
It will more likely be your sword, Antony.
又利又快
'Tis just as sharp and quicker...
谁都怕
...and frightened of heads.
今天元老院酒气冲天
There'll be a strong smell of wine in the Senate today.
连呼吸都要小心
We must breathe with restraint.
屋大维，凯撒之子名叫…
Octavian, this what's his name, this son of Caesar...
那令你不安吗？
...does it upset you?
不会
No.
你真是…
You run off at the mouth so...
惜话如金
...one thinks your words are as precious to you as your gold.
金石良言，要用得其所
Like my gold, I use them where they are worth most.
至于操守，我女友有个女友…
And your virtue? My friend has a friend.
那方面也一样
That too.
屋大难，当你死时…
You know, it's quite possible, Octavian, that when you die...
你会觉得白白浪费了这一生
...you will die without ever having been alive.
我会丢下你跟儿子不辞而别吗？
I can't leave without saying goodbye to my son and to you.
我跟你儿子认为…
We thought, your son and I, that if we came to you...
过来找你可以相处多几分钟
...we would have those few minutes more.
儿子，我要你记住…
A good thing to remember, my son:
只要不放弃，别人就夺不走
What you will not let go, no one will take from you.
小凯撒万岁，再见
Hail and farewell, little Caesar.
我包在地毯里被带到你面前 是一世纪前的事吗？
Was it a century ago when I was dropped at your feet, wrapped in a carpet?
还是昨晚的事？
Or was it last night?
何时派人来接我们？
When will you send for us? When?
- 很快 - 很快？有多快？什么时候？
-Soon. -How soon? When?
我回到罗马都需要不少时间
So much time must go by before even I reach Rome.
到底有多快？
And then how soon?
不容易，但不会太久
Within reasonable time.
何谓太久？
Time is never reasonable.
时间就是敌人
Time is our enemy, Caesar.
如果当是征服你会用什么策略？
Am I to conquer it for you? What plan of battle do you suggest?
我要带你儿子去罗马
I must bring your son to Rome.
罗马该见见凯撒之子…
Rome must see Caesar's son...
凯撒世界的未来统治者
...who will one day rule over Caesar's world.
凯撒？
Caesar?
风浪快将对你不利
I'm afraid the tides will soon be against you.
不只时间，连风浪也一样
Not only time, but the tides.
即使是神也无可奈何
Even as divinities, there seems little we can do about either.
但直到两年后
But only after more than two years...
经历了非洲和中亚无数战役
...and many wars in Africa and Asia Minor...
凯撒才得以渡海凯旋回意大利…
...was Сaesar able to cross over to Italy and come home at last...
治理国内的事
...to celebrate his triumphs and see to his affairs.
为表扬他所立的功劳 元老院兹授与凯撒…
"In recognition, the Senate has bestowed upon Caesar...
罗马终生独特领袖之荣衔
...the rank, privilege and title of dictator of Rome for life."
终生独裁领袖！
Dictator for life!
终于成为罗马真正的统治者
At long last, he is master of Rome.
阿波罗德斯，快去把事情准备好
Apollodorus, everything must be made ready at once.
船只、奴仆…
-Ships, servants-- -We've been ready for some time.
再没有不来迎接我们的借口了
Surely now nothing can prevent his sending for us...
即使只是受邀参观加冕典礼
...if only to attend his coronation as he did mine.
- 陛下… - 白白浪费了三年！
-Your Majesty-- -Three long, wasted years!
元老院为何等那么久
Why should the Senate have taken so long...
才宣告举世皆知的事实？
...to recognize what the world has already known?
凯撒早就是罗马的统治者
That Caesar was master of Rome.
鲁非欧想发表意见
Rufio wishes to speak.
陛下似乎有所误解
Your Majesty seems to misunderstand.
很明显凯撒已获授与独裁领袖
It seems quite clear. Caesar has been declared dictator of Rome for life.
罗马人眼中
True. However, to the Roman...
独裁领袖与统治者有很大分刖
...there is a vast difference between dictator and master.
无人能自称为罗马的统治者
No man can call himself master of Rome.
为什么不？
Why not?
换句话说罗马人不允许…
It has a meaning far too close to a word no Roman will tolerate:
国王存在
King.
那么做独裁领袖有何意义？
And to be dictator of Rome for life?
意味终身受罗马人民爱戴
Is to be granted the lifelong respect and honor of the Roman people.
独裁者能独裁何事？
And the dictates of the dictator?
事事皆要得到元老院同意
Must in each case, of course, be approved by the Senate of Rome.
谢谢你，鲁非欧
Thank you, Rufio.
敌人！敌人！敌人！ 敌人！敌人！敌人！
The enemy! The enemy! The enemy!
敌人！
Sosigenes.
我建议邀请克莉奥佩特拉 你一定觉得很奇怪
You must think it odd that I propose an invitation to Queen Cleopatra.
你觉得奇怪吗？
Do you?
埃及毕竟已正式与罗马结盟
Egypt, after all, has been officially declared ally of Rome.
但… 我还是讶异那么多人投赞成票
Still, I confess I was surprised at some of those who voted in favor.
你吃惊吗？
Were you?
非常感激今日受邀观礼
May I express my gratitude for being permitted to attend today's session?
见到众人根据自己的…
It was truly inspiring...
意愿行事令人印象深刻
...to witness the free will of free men so fearlessly expressed.
他极希望参加
He seemed most anxious to be present.
- 我认为不妨一试 - 你也这样认为吗？
-I saw no harm in granting him permission. -Didn't you?
今天总算见识到埃及的富有
After today, never again shall I doubt the extent of Egypt's wealth.
我不喜欢西塞罗的暗示
I don't like Cicero's implication.
埃及再有钱也买不到元老院一席
There's not enough gold in Egypt to buy the honor of a Roman senator.
但似乎足够买他那一票
More than enough, it seems, to buy his vote.
卜卦上说什么？
How was it now?
罗马将视他为王？
"Rome will know him in cloth of gold."
据报，街道上已万人空巷
According to reports, the reception in the streets has been extraordinary.
女王下令队伍缓慢前进
The queen has instructed the procession to move slowly...
迎合群众的喝采
...for the people's enjoyment.
克莉奥佩特拉准备俘虏罗马的人心
I might almost believe Cleopatra set out to capture the citizens of Rome.
的确如此
One would have every reason for believing exactly that.
罗谬勒斯和雷穆斯之后 从未见如此盛况
Nothing like this has come into Rome since Romulus and Remus.
他好大胆啊！
How unafraid he is.
那孩子好大胆啊！
她征服了罗马人民！
Your queen has conquered the people of Rome.
对了…没错
The people, yes.
走路要像个国王…抬头
Now then, walk like a king. Head up.
听群众欢呼
Listen to them cheer.
登上王座
Take your throne.
向左右两边答谢
Bow to the right, left.
不顺眼的，就目露凶光
Now an angry glance at someone who's displeased you.
很好，看到了没有 我都发抖了
Very good. I tremble. See me tremble?
不，不要露出微笑
No, don't smile.
这样他们就不怕你了
Not when they're trembling. It makes them stop.
现在，犯人会被一个个拉到你面前
Now the prisoners are dragged before you, one by one.
你要装出威严的样子 否则便没意义了
This one has no power anywhere, therefore means nothing.
要被认作高贵的统治者你要怎么说？
But you wish to be known as a noble ruler. What do you say?
我赦免你
I pardon you.
大声点赦免罪 要让大家都听到
Louder, boy. You pardon somebody, you want it known.
我赦免你
I pardon you!
这就对了 接下来是谁？
Ah, now, who comes here?
一个老朋友你信任他，但他背叛你
Once your friend. You trusted him, and he turned against you.
他有钱、有权、有家世
He has power, wealth and family.
他跪在你面前
He kneels. He begs you to be his friend again.
求你再信任他
To have you trust him again.
怎么办呢，小国王？
And then? What then, little king?
凯撒一定要先解决这当务之急？
Caesar must wish what needs commanding.
是要放干沼泽的水解除疟疾之害…
To drain the Pontine Marshes. To free Rome from malaria.
满足我的肚皮？
To fill my belly.
还是将泛滥的台伯河改道…
To control the Tiber's floods.
改善奥斯提港满足我的野心？
To improve the harbor at Ostia. To please my ambition.
不是为公众筑路、建图书馆…
And must I wish roads to be built, libraries for public use?
为解放的奴隶取得公民权？
The free men of Italy to be equal citizens to those of Rome?
其中许多是我们认可的德政
Many of these have merits and merit our approval.
你们认可的德政？ 凯撒是否像小学生一样
"Merit your approval." Is Caesar to come before the Senate each day...
每天向元老院交作业？
...like a schoolboy with his lessons, now passing, now failing?
难道可以不顾罗马人的福祉？
Do you suggest the Senate no longer deliberate the welfare of Rome?
你不想依法行事？
To end the process of Roman law?
我就是法律！ 我的话就是罗马人的福祉！
I must be the law! And my word must be the welfare of Rome.
不然，请取消这无意义的 独裁执政者衔头
Else, take from me this meaningless title of dictator.
我掌握政权已久
I've carried a sword for too long.
不能再空有其表了
I cannot now pretend with an empty scabbard.
凯撒应该记得授与你独裁者
Surely Caesar recalls the symbolic nature of the title "dictator"...
衔头的象征意义
...at the time it was conferred.
那是向你表达无上的荣耀…
It was to honor Caesar above all men...
以及罗马人对你战功的谢意
...and to indicate Rome's gratitude for Caesar's triumphs in its name.
我记得，布鲁特斯 而你记得那些战功吗？
Brutus, I recall them well, those triumphs.
记得那些战功吗？
Do you?
以法萨力亚为例
Pharsalia, for one. You trembled in Antony's hand...
当安东尼要依法…
...when Antony was hot to separate you from your head...
把你处死…
...with just cause.
是我下令饶你一命
My command spared your life.
没得商量的 并非只是意图，而是直接下令
There was no deliberating body. It was not my wish, but my command.
说清楚一点，就是独裁！ 你今天才得以满口大道理
By my dictate that you stand here dribbling virtue out of your mouth.
坐下
Sit down.
不，我不要无用的礼遇
No, I want no more meaningless privileges and considerations.
不要只有安抚作用的荣耀
No more honors designed to pacify me.
宁愿做个…
I would rather have nothing. Remain what I am at heart.
热心服务的平凡人
A humble man, anxious only to serve.
为何雕像的眼睛总是无神？
Why are the eyes of a statue always without life?
你们有没有人看过尼罗河？
Have any of you here seen the Nile?
找时间到那儿走一趟
Spare yourselves the journey.
看克莉奥佩特拉闪亮的眼神
She carries it within her eyes.
凯撒，时候不早了
I suggest, Caesar, that the hour is late.
对罗马人来说，很晚了
Very late for Rome.
我在说话啊，凯西尔斯！我…
I was speaking, Cassius! I was....
我说到哪里？
Now, where was I?
热心服务
"Anxious to serve."
我一辈子都在为群众服务
Yes, I’ve served. Served for all of my life.
为罗马打遍了半个地球
I've won for Rome more than half of the world.
你们今天的地位都是全因为我
Most of you owe your honors and fortunes to me.
现在，希望你们照我讲的话去做
And now I want you to do as I say.
尊我为…
You will appoint me...
罗马胪
...emperor of Rome.
无须再就座
There is no need to resume your seats.
仅代表众人感谢陛下款待
On behalf of all, thank you, Majesty, for your hospitality.
晚安
Good night.
多谢，晚安
Thank you and good night.
凯撒，他们后悔被召唤来这里 会议还是在元老院进行较恰当
They resent being summoned here for meetings properly held in the Senate.
后悔？
Resent it, do they?
我不懂…
I cannot understand...
雕像的眼是不会有神的
...that the eyes of a statue should be always without life.
他们恨我
They resent me.
因我太张扬
To flaunt me like this.
他们会阻挠你本该拥有的东西
They'll use it to keep from you that which is already yours.
靠天赋人权？不是吗？
By divine right, is that not so?
没错
Yes. It is.
就依天赋人权吧！
By divine right.
在元老院的会议中照样达成我的目标
We shall have the Senate, in its deliberations, deliberate that.
你确定你苦心追求的…
Are you quite sure what it is you want...
目标吗？
...so desperately?
一直非常确定
I've always been sure.
凯撒呢？
And Caesar?
谁能替他发言？
Does anyone speak for him?
谁都不能
No.
晚安
Good night.
站在由凯撒耸立在这里的新女神像…
Tell me, Brutus, is it proper to stand before this new goddess...
- 面前符合礼仪吗？ - 还是罗马人必须下跪？
-...Caesar has set here in the temple? -Or must we, as Romans, kneel?
看到了没有？ 旁边还有一个空着的神位
Not yet. See there, where room has been left for another deity?
当凯撒的神像在 克莉奥佩特拉的神像旁耸立好后…
When the god Caesar stands beside the goddess Cleopatra...
罗马人会匍匐在他俩面前
...then Rome will crawl before them.
事情要发生的话就必会发生
When that day comes, if it comes.
- 他要求被加冕为王 - 当晚提过一次，他神志不清
-He demanded we make him emperor. -Once. That one night, it was his sickness.
他神智会愈来愈差 终究将我们统统杀死
His sickness grows worse. In the end, it will kill us.
他一旦要求称帝之后便会自视为神！
He asked once to be made emperor, but he's since decreed himself a god!
是皇帝与神，不只是皇帝
Emperor and god. No longer just king, but emperor and god!
- 布鲁特斯，醒醒吧！ - 你要我怎么办？
-Brutus, open your eyes! -What do you want of me?
人民想到罗马的荣耀时
When the people think upon the honor of Rome...
想到的是布鲁特斯
...they think upon one man: He is Brutus.
背负那荣耀之责任
By that honor and by the responsibility you carry...
从凯撒的手中拯救罗马吧！
...Brutus, save Rome from Caesar!
你不能要求我毁了凯撒！
You cannot ask me to destroy him.
那就让凯撒毁了罗马吧！
Then let Caesar destroy Rome.
安东尼刚结束一场与我朋友的会议 明日元老院将宣布一项好消息
Antony has just come from a meeting of my friends with good news.
卢西尔斯明天将在元老院发动封我为王
Tomorrow at the Senate, Lucius Cotta will move that I be made king.
提案会被通过
It will pass.
我不明白
But I don't understand.
国王及皇帝
King and emperor.
会通过？
And it will pass?
过去几个月… 我悄悄运用
The last few months, I've been enjoying...
独裁者特权
...one of the few privileges of being dictator.
指派元老院议员
I have been appointing senators.
超过半数议员是我指派的
Slightly more than half the Senate has been appointed by me.
正如密斯里达的军队
Once again, the army of Mithradates...
你永远有备而来
...on its way all the time.
会通过的
It will pass.
明天，三月十五日将是…
Tomorrow, the ides of March, a day to be remembered...
我登上罗马王位的纪念日
...the Senate will declare me king of Rome.
没错，是国王，但非罗马王
King, yes, but not of Rome.
不是罗马王？什么意思？
Not of Rome? What are you saying?
他们准备称你为罗马帝国国王 但不包括意大利
They'll offer you king of the Roman Empire, outside Italy.
他们害怕…即使是你的朋友
They're afraid, Caesar. Even your friends.
害怕人民
Afraid of the people.
- 或许假以时日… - 怕人民
-Perhaps in time-- -To be afraid of the people.
因为人民浪费时间！
To waste time on the people.
除了罗马之外的国王？
King of all but Rome?
那还剩下什么？ 高卢的茅屋和不列颠的洞穴？
What is there? The huts of Gaul? The caves of Britain?
意大利以外的整个帝圈
The whole of the empire outside Italy.
我不能接受！
I will not accept.
他们只给个空壳
They mean it to be an empty gesture.
满足你的自大狂
Another title to please your fancy, flatter your ego.
所言不差
Nothing more.
真的会通过吗？
And it will pass.
那么接受他，凯撒
Then accept it, Caesar.
我从不接受一半的胜利
I have never settled for half a victory.
不会的，全能的凯撒
Nor will you now. Caesar, mighty Caesar...
我所讲的正是你教我的
...all I can say is what you've taught me:
不断蚕食，终能鲸吞！
Take a little, then a little more until finally you have it all.
让他们称你为王
Let them declare you king.
即使只有中亚的一颗树
Even if it's only of a tree in Asia Minor.
其他的会接踵而来！
The rest will come to you.
以前的经历再来一遍吗？
To redo once more everything I have already done?
未征服之地在等你呢！
It's what you have never done, what you never conquered that waits for you.
罗马帝胪馕Ь队将听命于你
The great legions of Rome in the outer empire that will become your legions.
埃及的黄金与权力，你的埃及
The gold, the power of Egypt. Your Egypt.
你可以征服并拥有全世界！
Caesar, you can conquer and hold the world as your own.
你不明白吗？
Won't you understand?
国王和神都不是选出来的
Kings are not elected. Gods are not elected.
我明了，不只罗马整个意大利半岛…
Why, not only Rome but all of Italy upon which Rome stands...
会像一滴汗珠滴进你手掌
...must fall in your hands like a drop of sweat.
随他们的意思封你为王
Let them make you what they choose.
我和我的部队都效忠于你
I'll serve with you. My legions with yours.
一起征服全世界 让亚历山大都自愧不如
Together we'll conquer a world beyond the wildest dreams of even Alexander.
苏拉死后是什么样子？
Rome. What was Rome when Sulla died...
夸萨斯在怕西亚战败后呢？
...when Crassus lost the armies in Parthia?
这些人会像吓坏的狗一样
These same men came after me through the streets...
跟在我后面 凯撒，救救我们！
...howling like frightened dogs, "Caesar, save us!"
到时，我还会不屑…
They would've made me king then.
他们称我为王
I wouldn't let them then.
他被丢进墙来，死状可怖
He was thrown over the wall. It's not a pretty sight.
钱庄老板泰塔斯！
Titus, the moneylender.
他为何被杀和被丢进来？
Why should he be killed savagely and brought here?
显然是警告我
Obviously, I am being warned.
说不定下一个是我
Perhaps I am next.
他们胆敢威吓你…
They dare to threaten you?
- 凯撒里奥！事发时他在哪里？ - 不远处
-Caesarion. Where was my son--? -Not far away.
他被吓着了
It frightened him.
- 雷彼德斯他现在有多少军队？ - 有十五队，但可能不只这数目
-Lepidus, how many legions has he now? -Fifteen. Perhaps more.
- 在哪里？ - 赛西亚
-Where? -Scythia.
你我今晚与雷彼德斯共进晚餐
You and I will dine with Lepidus tonight.
谈妥军队与作战 列清该杀的人的名单
We'll talk of armies and battlefields and lists of men to die.
明天元老院会议就随他们如何规划版图
Tomorrow in the Senate, let them offer the sands of Libya as my kingdom...
我一概接受
...I will accept.
这是凯撒
This is great Caesar...
受罗马爱戴的凯撒
...beloved by Rome...
我们有责任牺牲生命
...and at least one of us...
来维护罗马
...who must die so that Rome may live.
若果真的要这样做 就不必感到羞耻与恐惧
If it must be done, then let us do it unashamed and unafraid.
若罗马拒绝有个国王…
If the world is to know that it is Rome that will not have a king...
我们就自由、公然、光荣的… 在光天化日下去争取
...then let us make it the honorable act of free men in the light of day.
什么时候，布鲁特斯
In the light of what day, Brutus?
明天？
Tomorrow?
就在元老院会议上
In the curia of the Senate?
我们要带备武装吗？
And shall we be armed, all of us?
德西玛斯，你明天到凯撒家去 护送他到元老院
Decimus, come to Caesar's villa early tomorrow to escort him to the Senate.
辛巴，马克安东尼不能 跟凯撒一起进入会议室
Cimber, Marc Antony must not enter the curia with Caesar.
找藉口引开他或谈谈雷彼德斯家的事
On a pretext, lead him aside to speak of what you heard at Lepidus' house.
我想起一件奇怪的事
I remember something odd.
凯撒问过我们
At one point, Caesar asked of each of us...
喜欢什么死法
...what manner of death we would choose.
问到我时，他说
And Caesar, when it came to him, looked straight at me and said:
猝死？
"Sudden."
很奇怪吧？
Odd, isn't it?
我以为你还在睡觉
I was afraid I'd find you still asleep.
凯撒里奥还在睡 他昨晚睡不着
Caesarion is. He was awake most of the night.
暴风雨吓着他了？
Did the storm frighten him?
他说没有，但他真的吓坏了
He said not, but it did. I could tell.
有时间进来吗？
Have you time to come in?
德西玛斯正在等着 他要送我去元老院
Decimus awaits. He came by expressly to accompany me to the Senate.
德西玛斯？他以前有这么做吗？
Decimus? Has he done this before?
狡诈的政治家
A shrewd politician.
在这特别的日子他希望与我同行 以提高他的身价
He hopes to benefit by arriving with me, this day of days.
让安东尼紧随你身边
Keep Antony close by.
你也是？
You too?
罗马女人今日都忐忑不安
The ladies of Rome seem to have caught each other's fears this morning.
好像传染病一样
Like a head cold.
卡普妮雅今天还求我不要到元老院
Calpurnia pleaded with me not to go to the Senate at all.
她为何不想你去？
Why? Why would she not want you to go?
只是昨夜的恶劣天气
Oh, the bad night. Nothing else.
她尖叫着从梦中惊醒
She awoke screaming in her sleep. The thunder, the lightning.
她梦见我被谋杀
She dreamed that she saw me murdered. That she saw me...
我，或我的雕像，全身都是血
...or a statue of me covered in blood.
仆人告诉她看见天堂有人身体着火
The servants told her of seeing men of fire in the heavens...
怪事连连
...odd happenings and so forth.
广场上看见怪鸟
Strange birds were seen in the Forum.
一只飞进元老院 衔着月桂枝
One flew into the Senate carrying a sprig of laurel which it dropped...
放在庞培的雕像上
...at the base of Pompey's statue.
庞培？
Pompey?
- 凯撒，我好害怕！ - 你该不会叫我避开吧？
-Caesar, I'm afraid. -You must not tell me to stay away.
我也该害怕吗？
Shall I too be afraid?
凯撒能因为暴风雨 而放弃他的江山吗？
Can it be said of Caesar, he gave up the world because of a thunderstorm?
他的神威竟向迷信屈服？
That such divinity that was in him ran before mortal superstition?
我觉得你需要我
I feel you need me now...
而我却帮不上忙
...and I cannot help you.
那就帮我像以往般活下去 有别于众人…
Then help me to live as I have lived, always differently from the rest.
一辈子在贪生怕死里苟且偷安
The others, for whom life is merely an endless fear of dying.
愿众神…
Your gods...
与你同在，凯撒
...and mine go with you, Caesar.
除你之外，世上尽是小人
The world, except for you, is filled with little men.
烈火熊熊
Fire burns.
狂风不断
The winds of destruction blow.
坚强
Rome...
孤寂的罗马狂风不断袭击你！
...mighty and alone, the winds of destruction blow down upon thee!
暴风、冰雹
Storms and hail shall cut down wheat...
摧毁五谷、飞禽… 以及天下万物
...shall cut down birds and living things of earth.
连天上众神
The heavens...
都难以幸免
...and the gods themselves.
我的儿子！
My son!
凯撒！凯撒！
Caesar! Caesar!
凯撒！凯撒！凯撒！…
我迟了，太多事要办了
I would've come sooner. There was much to do.
你做得很好
And it seems you have done it extremely well.
就是这里吗？
Is that where--?
对
Yes.
在埃及，我们为英雄建纪念碑
In Egypt, we build eternal monuments to our dead heroes.
你们则像烧垃圾般把他烧掉
Here, you burn them like rubbish.
再见
Goodbye.
我带来几个十号军团的人 你很安全，不必害怕
I've brought the 10th Legion and Rufio. You have nothing to fear.
即使不必害怕也没有理由留下
Nothing to fear? That's no reason for staying.
太多事发生得太快
So much has happened so quickly.
必须收拾残局
Suddenly I have the pieces of a broken world to pick up:
一定要乘夜出走吗？
Caesar, you running off at night like this.
为什么我要留下来？
Do you suggest that I stay? Why?
我累得无法解释
Don't ask me to be clear about my feelings right now. I’m tired.
即使精神爽利 我想也没法完全表达
And with you, it's never easy to say my meaning.
但你表达得很好，安东尼
But you speak so well, Antony.
听说你宣读凯撒遗嘱时很激动
I've been told how excitingly you read Caesar's will...
向哭泣着的凶手 自由、民主的罗马人民宣读
...to the sobbing, murdering, free citizens of Rome.
指定他侄儿屋大维继位！
Naming as his heir his great nephew, Octavian!
我懂得凯撒的心愿与理由！
I knew Caesar's will and the reasons for it.
若不指定屋大维继位
If Octavian hadn't been named...
你们母子还能活多久？
...how many hours or minutes would you and your son have survived?
如果凯撒是国王
And if Caesar had become truly king...
他会指定屋大维吗？
...do you believe he would still have named Octavian?
无论如何，事情已结束了
In any case, it's over.
凯萨…
Caesar...
他的梦想跟他一并被谋杀
...and the dream that was murdered with him.
先是亚历山大的梦想
First Alexander's...
然后是凯撒的…
...then Caesar's.
都结束了
Now over. Finished.
- 首先，罗马必须恢复秩序 - 又是罗马
-First, Rome must be put in order. -Rome again.
布鲁特斯等凶手已逃脱了几个
Brutus, Cassius and the others must be found and killed.
- 必须逮捕回来处死 - 然后呢？
-Then? -Then in death...
凯撒死后理应享有生前应得的封号 甚至被奉为神明
...Caesar must be granted the power and title he was denied in life. Deified, even.
过世的国王，死去的神明 现在罗马安全了
A dead king, a dead god. Safe enough even for Rome.
凯撒之子，凯撒里奥 有权要求受封为胪跤肷衩
Caesarion as Caesar's son could claim both the title of king and his deification.
又是哪个执法单位会执行这项授舆？
And to what court of law would my son and I take our claim?
我会亲自向元老院提议
I will present it to the Roman Senate myself.
我相信你会这样做
I believe you would.
被议士们讪笑之后…
And after the noble senators have stopped laughing...
我们母子是否该向罗马宣战？
...do my son and I then declare war on Rome?
不，这需要另一位凯撒
No. For this, a Caesar would be needed.
你时间有限
You have very little time.
另一位凯撒
Another Caesar.
谢谢你，我不会忘记你的恩情
But thank you. I shall remember your kindness to us.
- 你太轻易放弃了 - 是吗？
-You give up too easily. -Do I?
我到亚历山卓再与你详谈
Let me come to Alexandria and talk more with you.
- 随时欢迎 - 可能的话，就是今晚
-Whenever you like. -Now. Tonight, if I could.
只要你铭记在心中
In any case, try to remember.
（中场休息）
安东尼追捕行刺凯撒的凶手 差不多有两年时间
For more than two years did Antony seek out the assassins of Caesar.
他与凯撒的继位者
At last, at Philippi...
屋大维合力 终于在菲利比
...he was able to set against them his legions and those of Octavian...
与叛党对垒
...who was Caesar's heir.
凯西尔斯第一个自杀
Cassius was the first to die...
身亡
...by his own hand.
接下来是布鲁特斯以及其他人
Then Brutus and the others.
安东尼万岁！
Hail Antony!
安东尼之军万岁！
Hail Antony's legion!
记得，菲利比之仗
You remember Philippi.
是他打胜的
He won it.
阁下
My lord.
- 这边请 - 但我的帐蓬在这边
-This way. -But my tent is this way.
稍后再见他屋大维令我心生沮丧
Later. I'll see him later. Octavian depresses me.
你答应过的
You promised.
战事结束，我们赢了
Well, the fighting's over. We've won it all.
你会迅速恢复健康
Your health should improve quickly now.
就算死也该与你一起战死沙场
Even if I die, my place is with you on the field.
- 你不该拦着我 - 凯撒病得无法上马
-You were wrong to prevent me. -Caesar was ill.
凯撒？哦，我又忘了
Caesar? Ah, yes. I keep forgetting.
我也继承了他的名字，改名凯撒
I have inherited the name. I have made it mine.
有何不可？反正不会搞乱
Why not? You'll never be confused with the other one.
至少你的队伍在我指挥下骁勇善战
At least your troops fought bravely, under my command.
亚格里巴已告诉我了
Agrippa has kept me fully informed.
海军将领为何在此？
What were you doing there?
这是陆地上的肉搏战 不是海上的大船相撞
The battle was fought on land, between men, not wood bumping on water.
你因为预测会下大两 而带他来的吗？
Why did you bring Agrippa? Were you expecting rain?
要不要选块靓地，我们单对单？
Shall we choose a piece of land, just you and I?
不准多言 我们有事要谈
Be quiet. There are matters to talk about.
你反对亚格里巴留下吗？
Have you an objection to Agrippa remaining?
我永远反对亚格里巴
I object to Agrippa at all times.
无奈的躺在这里
Lying here, indisposed...
你有很多时间考虑那个问题
...you must have had time to consider the problem.
我想最好继续由三巨头执政
I think it is best to continue the Triumvirate.
你、我和雷彼德斯
You and I and Lepidus.
好啊
Very well.
雷彼德斯管非洲和各岛屿 你主掌西班牙和高卢
Lepidus shall have Africa and the islands. You, Spain and Gaul.
罗马和意大利则三人共治
Rome and Italy to be administered by the three of us, jointly.
- 你呢？ - 其他的归我管理
-And you? -All the rest.
雷彼德斯在非洲，你在东方
Then, with Lepidus in Africa and you in the East...
恢复意大利罗马的秩序 就变成我的问题
...bringing order to Rome and Italy will be my problem.
- 看起来是如此 - 西班牙和高卢的税收不足
-So it seems. -Spain and Gaul aren't enough.
我需要钱
I'll need money.
- 罗马又已经有抗税暴动 - 我听说了
-There have been tax riots in Rome. -So I’ve heard.
说定了
Done.
一言为定
And done.
你认为凯撒会同意吗？
Would Caesar approve, do you think?
当然，可能埃瑟丝的黑面纱 会令他不高兴
Definitely. Perhaps the veil of Isis would have bothered him a bit.
三年了
Three years...
罗马人只记得金币上他的头像
...and Rome remembers him only by the image on a gold coin.
我带回来的那种金币吗？
Are they those I brought back with me?
屋大维下令铸造
When Octavian had them struck off...
以纪念凯撒的神威
...it was to commemorate Caesar's deification.
顺便连神威也继承
So that he could inherit Caesar's divinity together with all the rest.
神死后也无法改遗嘱
Even a dead god cannot rewrite his will.
安东尼有向元老院提议 封凯撒里奥为王
Antony did present Caesarion's claims to the Senate.
他实现了部分诺言
He kept that much of his promise.
他亦将实现其他的
And he will keep the rest of it.
凯撒过世已三年
After almost three years since Caesar's death...
菲利比之战也过了一年
...more than a year since Philippi?
安东尼会来，他需要埃及
Antony will come. He will need Egypt.
埃及就是你
Egypt is you.
正是这个意思，安东尼需要我
That's what I meant, of course. Antony will need me.
谈钱就令我头痛
Finances! My head hurts when you talk of money.
换个话题吧
Change the subject.
罗马消息
All right. News from Rome.
屋大维逼雷彼德斯出走
Octavian has forced Lepidus out of his command and into exile.
真后悔喝了那么多酒
I wish I hadn't-- I wish I had not drunk so much today.
我也是
So do I.
我令你担心吗，鲁非欧？
Do I trouble you, Rufio?
是的
Yes, you do.
凯撒从不酒醉 没有事能让他头昏
I'll wager Caesar was never befuddled by wine. Nothing befuddled Caesar
安东尼，跟帕西亚之争将是苦战
The campaign against Parthia won't be easy.
- 我们还剩多少部队？ - 难以估计
-How many legions have we left? -It's hard to tell.
- 逃兵很多，实力偏低 - 逃兵？
-So many desertions. -Desertions?
出不到军饷
They haven't been paid in months.
记得我们入侵希腊时吗？
You remember when we started into Greece?
我跟士兵同住同食
I lived with them, ate with them. I was one of them.
现在跟他们距离好远，远得像回忆
They seem distant to me now, as if they were a memory.
我们必须有钱出军饷
We must find the gold to pay them...
粮食、补给、战舰、盔甲…
...the wheat to feed them, supplies, ships, armor.
说得容易，何来有钱？
And where do you suggest we look for all these?
- 或许，在往东一点… - 叙利亚？
-I thought perhaps further to the east. -Syria?
- 或许稍稍往南一点 - 伊索匹亚？
-Perhaps more to the south. -Ethiopia?
稍微往北一点…
To the north--
- 不准你提她 - 我没有啊！
-I forbid you to mention her! -I didn't.
- 我不会像乞丐一样爬着去找她 - 为什么她没有主动资助？
I won't crawl to her! Why hasn't she offered assistance?
- 或许她不知道 - 她当然知道，她无所不知
-She may not know. -She knows everything.
- 就算为答应我为她所做的一切… - 或许她想亲自表达
-If only out of gratitude-- -Perhaps she'll express it in person.
让她来找我，我那么不如凯撒吗？
Then let her come to me. Am I so much less than Caesar?
她贵为埃及女王，而且你答应过…
Nor is she less than Cleopatra, queen of Egypt, and you promised--
女王！女王！脱光衣服还不是女人？
Queen. Strip them naked, they're no longer queens.
裸体将军又如何识别阶级？
It is also difficult to tell the rank of a naked general.
没军队的将军无异裸体
And generals without armies are naked, indeed.
好吧，折衷一下
All right. I'll meet her halfway.
我派你
I'll send you to her.
- 命令她来见我 - 如果是命令我就不必去了
-You order her to come. -If I am to order her, I need not journey.
- 那么就召见她 - 那更不好
-Then summon her. -Even worse.
那就求她、拜托她 诱惑她随你怎说
Then beg, entreat, cajole, find the word you like...
洒香水、扮思春总之叫她来见我！
...pour perfume, whinny like a stallion. But see that she comes to me.
我明白你的处境
I understand your position, Rufio.
当然你也了解我的
Surely you must understand mine.
我不想加入他众多妃嫔之中
I do not intend to join that long list of queens...
幸得安东尼恩宠就高兴得发抖
...who have quivered happily at being summoned by Lord Antony.
我并不是说召见
But surely I didn't say "summoned."
你说邀请他的意思就是召见
You said "invite." He meant "summon."
再说，我也是埃及女王
In any case, I am the queen of Egypt.
我想留在埃及国土内
And I choose to remain on Egyptian soil.
塔瑟斯并不远，陛下
Tarsus is not the other end of the world, Your Majesty.
离开埃及一步就算远了
If it were one step from Egypt, that would be too far.
我只会在埃及
I will meet with Lord Antony...
见安东尼阁下
...but only on Egyptian soil.
总要找个两全其美的地方
My lady, a way must be found, a time, a place to satisfy you both.
一定要这样吗，鲁非欧？
Must it, Rufio?
克莉奥佩特拉？
Cleopatra.
克莉奥佩特拉！
Cleopatra!
是的
It is.
一定是！
It must be.
她说除非在埃及，否则绝不
She said never, except on Egyptian soil.
当女人说绝不时…
"Never." Something women say to begin with.
代我迎接克莉奥佩特拉！
Welcome Queen Cleopatra on my behalf.
在这种状况之下… 宫里今晚加办舞会来欢迎她
Extend my invitation to a banquet in her honor.
- 你不认为可能… - 你还不信啊，鲁非欧？
-Don't you think--? -Still not convinced Rufio?
快点，很多事要忙叫厨师来见我
Hurry back, there's much to be done. Have the cooks sent to me.
对不起，鲁非欧，你搞错了
Forgive me, noble Rufio. It is you who do not understand.
女王在船舱里就仍算是在埃及领土
Queen Cleopatra, at present in her chamber, is on Egyptian territory...
她不打算落船
...and intends to remain on it.
容我提醒你
Most learned Sosigenes, forgive me...
这里是塔瑟斯 不是亚历山卓
...but this is Tarsus, not Alexandria.
你是在塔瑟斯，而我在埃及
You are on Tarsus, noble Rufio. I am on Egypt.
今明两晚，安东尼若想见陛下
Tonight and tomorrow night, if Lord Antony desires to meet Her Majesty...
欢迎他莅临埃及
...he will come to her, to Egypt.
我会设法说服安东尼前来
I shall do my best, learned friend, to prevail upon Lord Antony to attend.
马克安东尼，你动作真快
Marc Antony, how prompt you are.
不快就不可原谅了
If I had not been, it would be unforgivable of me.
我一直在这里等你登船
I had hoped to be here to welcome you as you came aboard.
这件事一样不可原谅
If you had been, it would be unforgivable of me.
别太严肃，偶然放纵一下自己
Be more tolerant. Forgive yourself now and then.
三年了，你怎么会愈来愈美艳？
Almost three years. Have you possibly become more beautiful?
三年了吗？
Almost three? That long?
时间过得真快
The time has passed so quickly.
你的项链上，好像是金币
Your necklace. It seems to be made of gold coins.
凯撒的金币
Coins of Caesar.
- 好看吗？ - 很好看
-Do you find it attractive? -Very.
你穿着得像个…
And I find what you're wearing most becoming.
希腊人
Greek, isn't it?
我喜欢希腊的东西
I have a fondness for almost all Greek things.
我有希腊血统，多谢你的奉承
As an almost all-Greek thing, I'm flattered.
罕见的项链
An unusual necklace.
全由凯撒金币造咸
Nothing but gold coins of Caesar.
- 哪儿买的？ - 我订造的
-How did you come by it? -I had it made.
一直戴在身上
I wear it always.
令人赞叹的宴会
A fabulous feast.
搭船航行总是会觉得不自在
One is so limited when one travels by ship.
华丽的船
This fabulous ship...
加上艳丽的女王
...together with its queen, the fabulous Cleopatra.
马克安东尼绝非寂寂无名之人
The name of Marc Antony is not exactly unknown to the world.
- 为何一两年前相会以来… - 快三年了
-In the last year or so since we met-- -Almost three.
如今是三分之一个罗马巨头
By now you have become one-third the master of Rome.
你就是不许自己忘了他吗？
You don't permit yourself to forget him, is that it?
不许自己，这话真奇怪
That's an odd way of putting it. "Don't permit myself"?
非把他戴在颈上不可吗？
Is it necessary to wear him around your neck?
你忘了三年来
You forget, Antony, in these almost three years...
你的日子多充实
...how full your own life has been.
独力统治，你也不可能闲着
They can't have been uneventful for you. You rule Egypt alone.
很忙，但不充实
Oh, they have been busy, but not full.
两者并不一样
There's a difference.
白天时间永远都不够…
There cannot be enough hours in the days of a queen...
晚上却是长夜漫漫
...and her nights have too many.
- 只好靠回忆来填满 - 回忆凯撒？
-So I fill them with memories. -Of Caesar?
他，以及他…
And of a dream...
几乎实现的梦想
...that almost came true.
你可能记得…
You may remember.
我记得那天晚上在罗马似乎仍能实现
I remember that night in Rome, saying it could still come true.
那晚你跟许多人说了许多话
You said so much that night to so many.
我已将他们打发走了
Let me get rid of them all.
为什么？我事先安排了希腊舞
Why? I have arranged an entertainment.
以便欢迎希腊酒神
A dance in the Greek fashion to welcome the god Bacchus.
若我走，他们全都会离席
If I make a great show of going, they'll have to leave too.
我再回来
Then I can return...
我们可以… 私下谈谈，只有你和我
...and we can talk alone, you and I.
- 你何时回来？ - 一小时，最多两小时
-When would you return? -In an hour, no more than two.
- 你会留多久？ - 直到无话可谈为止
-How long would you stay? -Until we had nothing more to say.
你是游泳健将吗？我们黎明起航
Are you a strong swimmer? We sail at sunrise.
我不懂
I don't understand.
回亚历山卓，回埃及
Home to Alexandria, to Egypt.
你老远跑来停留一晚 只为嘲弄我！
You've come all this way for one night. All to make a fool of me.
留下来过夜
Perhaps you would feel less a fool...
可会不那么像被嘲弄？
...if you stayed the night with me, is that it?
我说过
I've told you before.
在你面前我变得 难以用说话表达自己
With you, words do not come easily to me.
我心里很多话说不出来
There is too much unsaid within me that I cannot say.
你不说我怎知道
Then I cannot know it.
你也有很多说不出的话吧
There is much unsaid within you too.
可能每个人都一样
That is probably true of everybody.
留一会儿吧
Stay for a while.
相识虽久，相知不多，给我时间
I have known you so long but so little. Give me time.
我不能，罗马和埃及加起来…
Not I. Not Egypt and Rome together.
即使神也无法给你时间
Not even the gods have time to give you.
但是，安东尼，你应把握时势
But, Antony, use what you have.
不要在塔瑟斯陪诸神游戏
Don't waste it by playing at god here in Tarsus...
而屋大维在罗马快变成神了
...while Octavian in Rome becomes a god.
舞会应该结束了吧
The dance, I take it, is over.
起来
Sit up.
我看你是不是戴着回忆入睡
I want to see whether you sleep with your memories.
心中有话说不出口…
With so much left unsaid within you...
活动手脚有助纾缓压力
...it must be a relief to break and tear things.
- 我现在有话要说 - 改天吧
-I want to say something now. -Perhaps some other time.
现在！
Now!
凯萨
Caesar.
征伐再征伐…
Conquer and conquer.
世界都臣服于脚下
Bring the world to its knees.
却仍不是凯撒，你明白吗？
"You're not a Caesar. Did you know that?"
勇冠三军…
Be braver than the bravest...
智慧过人，却仍不是凯撒
...stronger than the strongest. Still no Caesar.
不管怎努力，凯撒都早你一步
Caesar's done it first and better. Ruled better, loved better, fought better.
不管统治、德政、战略他都优胜于你
Run where you will, you can't get out. There's no way out.
不管走到哪里，都无路可逃 永远笼罩在凯撒的阴影下！
The shadow of Caesar will cover you and cover the universe for all of time.
你在罗马时说
"Whenever you like," you said in Rome.
随时欢迎到亚历山卓来
"Come to Alexandria whenever you like."
我说就是今晚
"Now, tonight," I said.
向凯撒为你安排的王位致敬
To bow to the throne upon which Caesar put you.
谈论新战术 那是凯撒无法超越还抄袭的
To talk of a new treaty. Caesar's can't be improved. Copy it.
谈凯撒之子 谈至今犹在，你们共同的梦想
Of Caesar's son. Of the dream you shared with Caesar that still fills your life.
亚历山卓是你们 向世界发号施令的地方
Alexander's design for a world to be ruled by you and Caesar.
马克安东尼何在？
Where is Antony?
Where is Marc Antony?
伟大的安东尼！神圣的安东尼！
Antony the Great! The divine Antony!
他在此
Here.
他
He's...
在此
...here.
迟凯撒一步… 就在凯撒的右手…
One step behind Caesar. At the right hand of Caesar.
在凯撒的阴影里
In the shadow of Caesar.
在他之后，有多少人爱过你？
Tell me, how many have loved you since him?
一个？十个？所有人？ 还是一个都没有？
One? Ten? Anyone? No one?
他们吻你时是凯撒的唇碰你吗？ 黑暗中你呼唤的是他的名字？
Have they kissed you with Caesar's lips? Is it his name you cry out in the dark?
之后…他是否回来找你？ 你是否向回忆请求原谅？
Afterwards, has he reproached you and have you begged forgiveness?
借酒壮胆，自怜自艾
You've come here, then, running over with wine and self-pity...
这算是征服凯撒？
...to conquer Caesar.
长久以来，我生命中充满了你
For so long now, you've filled my life...
像心中随时听见的噪音
...like a great noise I hear everywhere in my heart.
我要摆脱你，不想你…
I want to be free of you, of wanting you...
不想再担惊受怕
...of being afraid.
恐怕凯撒不会答应
Yet, Caesar would not permit it.
但我永远
But I will never...
忘不了你
...be free of you.
当你乘坐大石兽
From the first instant I saw you...
抵达罗马时…
...entering Rome on that monstrous stone beast...
石兽在太阳下闪耀
...shining in the sun...
像金色的小玩具
...like a little gold toy.
我很忌妒凯撒
...how I envied Caesar.
我突然生病了
Went suddenly sick with it.
不是他的战功，不是他的头衔
Not his conquests or his triumphs.
不是群众的欢呼…
Not his titles or the roaring of the mob.
而是因为你而妒忌他
I envied him you.
第一次在罗马见到你我就记得你
When we first met in Rome, I remembered you.
并觉得永世难忘
I wondered that I could ever have forgotten.
难忘我？
Remembered me?
多年前，你还是个骑兵军宫的时候
Years ago, when you were a young cavalry officer...
驻守在亚历山卓宫殿旁
...stationed at the palace in Alexandria under that fat Roman general.
指挥官是个胖将军他叫什么名字？
-What was his name? -Gabinius.
加比尼尔斯
Gabinius.
我当时十二岁，已经爱上你
I was 12 years old, and I loved you.
- 胡说 - 真的
-Nonsense. -It's true.
相恋之人总希望未曾爱过
Lovers always want so much never to have loved before.
很可能如此
It's possible, you know.
揣测谁先爱谁，便成了游戏
It becomes a game. Who loved whom first?
我就猜过
I did.
当初若见过我，你一定很怕我
If you noticed me at all then, you were probably terrified of me.
是啊，大家说罗马人会杀小孩
With good reason. Everybody knows Romans cut up little children...
并拿来喂马
...and feed them to their horses.
我们把这次当是一个开始
We'll make this our beginning.
从今夜起
Beginning with tonight...
你不能再忌妒凯撒
...you must never envy Caesar...
或任何人，任何事
...or anyone, anything again.
毕竟
After all...
这不是新闻
...this is nothing new.
多年以来…
For so many years...
安东尼一直是
...Antony has fed upon the crumbs...
朱利斯凯撒的爪牙
...that fell from Julius Caesar's table.
我认为…
I say...
干柴烈火
...they are deserving of each other.
就让他们留在埃及…
Let him stay in Egypt.
虚耗生命好了
Let him fritter away his life as he chooses...
但罗马人的财产和政府却不能虚耗
...but not the possessions and the empire of the Roman people!
罗马人！
The Roman people!
什么是罗马人的荣耀与财产？
The Roman people. What are glory and possessions to them?
只要安东尼高兴
Is their Antony content?
他们就高兴
Then so are they.
安东尼有没有将帝国
Does their Antony sweep their empire...
置于克莉奥佩特拉床下？
...under Cleopatra's bed?
爱戴他的罗马人只会叹口气 还是随他高兴！
His adoring Romans sigh and remain content.
无论距离多远
Let him stay however distant for however long...
多久没有想起他们…
...with never a thought of them.
罗马人还是敬爱他
The Roman people hold him close to their hearts.
远？
Distant?
或许离罗马很远
Perhaps from Rome but not from Caesar, I think.
但离凯撒及凯撒之子不远
Nor from Caesar's son.
朱曼尼卡斯，你说我吗？
Germanicus, do you speak of me?
不，屋大维，我说凯撒
No, Octavian, I speak of Caesar.
我也是凯撒
I am Caesar.
只有当安东尼
Only while Antony remains...
远离罗马时
...distant from Rome.
安东尼
Antony!
不会在亚历山卓逗留太久
Stay not too long in Alexandria!
朱曼尼卡斯
Germanicus...
不会在罗马逗留太久
...stay not too long in Rome.
- 此事安东尼知道多少？ - 都知道，或许更多
-How much of this is known to Antony? -All of it and more.
我定期以书面通知他状况
I've written him regularly. Letters, dispatches by personal messenger.
他怎回答？
And what has he answered?
他回答说他对政治不再有兴趣
He wrote he was no longer interested in the matters I described.
他也不想回罗马
That he would not return to Rome.
他对可能的损失相当清楚
That he understood quite clearly what was at stake, what he would lose.
但他不愿意离开你
But that he would not leave you.
啊，对了，试试山羊的
Let's try the goat.
好啦，再试一次山羊的 这边，不要太多
Let's have that goat again. There. Not too much.
这边
There.
牛奶
The milk of a cow...
羊奶、驴奶哪一种最能软化胡须？
...of a goat and of an ass. Which is best for softening the beard?
屋大维一星期才刮一次胡子 是真的吗？
Is it true Octavian shaves but once a week?
即使如此一阵风就吹光他的汗毛
Even then, he has merely to face the wind and let the fuzz blow away.
你知道朱曼尼卡斯从罗马来了吗？
You knew, didn't you, Germanicus was here from Rome?
知道
Yes.
你喜欢胡须吗？ 我年轻时留过胡子，亮红色的
Have you strong feelings about beards? I had one. Bright red.
你为何不见他？
Why haven't you seen him?
你一去…
When you go...
要很久吗？
...must it be for very long?
我要带些海绵回去
I must take some of these with me. They don't have them.
以前我在罗马时
At least, they didn't when I was last...
没这东西
...in Rome.
他们为我挖陵寝时…
While they were digging the foundation of my tomb...
找到一面古墙
...the workers found an old wall.
有些有几百年的文字：
Someone had scratched on it hundreds of years ago:
你昨晚没来，我无法入睡
"You were not here last night, and I could not sleep.
今晚你会来吗？
Will you be here tonight?"
你想他们有否再见面？
Do you suppose they ever met again?
目前我想捉住的、看到的… 拥有的、为之存在的…
Everything that I shall ever want to hold or look upon or have or be...
只有与你同在这里
...is here now with you.
我也不想对不起自己
I must not be sorry for myself.
对此事，女王并不比 国王或王子占优势
Queens are sometimes no better at that than kings, or even princes.
不公平
It doesn't seem fair.
现在的感觉我早在
What I feel I should have felt long ago when I was very young.
年轻时感受过
When I could say to myself that this was how love was...
当时我想爱就该是这样
...and how it would be.
但在长久的等待后忽然觉悟
But to have waited so long, to know so suddenly...
在这么久以后…
...this late...
爱会伤人，锥心之痛
...how it hurts. How love can stab the heart.
小心屋大维
Be careful with Octavian.
他该小心我
Let him be careful with me.
罗马不希望你俩开战
The Romans want no war between the two of you.
再说，你还未准备好
In any case, you are not ready yet.
世界充满爱，不会再有战争
War? The world is filled with love. There'll be no more wars.
你该得到你应得的
You must have your share.
头衔、权利应该确立清楚
Your titles and powers must be spelled out exactly.
在东方你该有绝对的权威
There can be no question of your complete authority in the East.
安东尼，我日子该怎么过？
Antony, how will I live?
跟我一样过
The same as I.
彼此每交换一个气息…
One breath upon the other.
我们的距离
Each bringing us...
每拉近了一点
...one breath closer.
你一离开，我就魂不守舍
You take so much of me with you so far.
记住记住，他们要你忘记我
Remember, remember. They'll want you to forget.
怎么忘记？
-Please-- -Forget? How?
我一步…
I can never be more far away from you...
都不离开
...than this.
他会先到布林迪森
He will come first to Brindisium.
亚格里巴和我计划盛大迎接他
Agrippa and I plan to welcome his arrival with a great ceremony.
安东尼该知道罗马人…
Antony must see how dear to the hearts of the Romans, of us all...
包括我们，是多么敬爱他
...he is and has been.
他离开了一段很长的时间
He has been away for a very long time.
或许可以劝他多留一会
Perhaps we can persuade him to stay with us even longer.
有可能，屋大维雅 如果你来布林迪森会有帮助
Perhaps, Octavia, if you came to Brindisium, you could help.
你可能忘记了 还未到六个月…
You may have forgotten. It is only six months since--
请亚格里巴和祖先饶恕你
Begging the pardon of Agrippa and our ancestors...
我不同意年轻寡妇该放弃生活
...I do not agree that a young widow must retire from life.
丈夫过世后，你从未离开过我家
You haven't left my house since your husband died.
若只是为着健康，这改变就…
If only for the sake of your health, the change alone....
那么，请亚里格巴和祖先饶恕
Then, begging the pardon of Lord Agrippa and our ancestors...
我期待这个改变
...I would look forward very much to the change.
没人像她那样明艳动人
Nothing, no one, could possibly shine more brightly in the sun.
不只安东尼
Not only Antony.
每个人都想染指屋大维雅
I know of no man who would not hold out his greedy fists for Octavia.
这个人质足够
After all, what greater pledge could I offer...
表达诚意了吧？
...of my goodwill toward him?
为了和平他不得
And how could Antony better show his love of peace and Rome...
不接受
...than by accepting?
克莉奥佩特拉呢？
And Cleopatra?
你建议请她参加婚礼？
Are you suggesting we invite her to the wedding?
记得她在罗马时
You remember when Julius Caesar returned...
朱利斯凯撒的下场吗？
...and those months while she was in Rome?
他的心中、脑里都有毒
There was a poison in his heart, in his brain.
我知道他有癫痫症
Yes, the falling sickness. But more than that.
- 但克莉奥佩特拉是主因 - 我记得很清楚
-Cleopatra. -I remember well.
- 安东尼不是凯撒 - 这点我很感激
-Antony is no Caesar. -I am grateful for that.
就算他与屋大维雅成婚 他会忘了克莉奥佩特拉吗？
Granted that he marries Octavia, will he forget Cleopatra?
- 她又会允许他忘记吗？ - 不大可能会
-Will she permit him to forget? -Most probably not.
- 我能说话吗？ - 快告诉我
-Have I permission to speak? -Tell me, quickly.
布林迪森传来的罗马消息
A galley came to Pelusium with news from Rome.
安东尼与屋大维达成重大协议
Antony and Octavian have sealed a great pact.
安东尼多掌握十队军队和整个东方
Antony has 10 more legions and all of the East for his domain.
将宣布罗马与埃及结盟
Egypt will be declared ally of Rome.
成功了！
It is done.
- 还有其他消息… - 不，没有了，阁下
-There is more. -No. No more, my lord.
- 他害怕 - 还有其他消息吗？
-He's afraid. -Is there anything more?
陛下请恕罪，有一场婚事
Forgive me, Divine Majesty. There has been a marriage.
一场政治婚姻
A marriage of state.
屋大维凯撒之妹
Between Octavia, the sister of Caesar...
屋大维雅与安东尼结婚
...and Lord Antony.
还有其他事吗？
Anything more?
他们目前在雅典
They're presently in Athens.
一年内，屋大维雅会回罗马
Sometime within the year, Lady Octavia is to return to Rome.
安东尼会来签署结盟条约
Antony will come Alexandria to negotiate the alliance of Rome and Egypt.
退下
Leave me.
不
No.
全部退下
Completely alone.
安东尼！
Antony!
你喜欢这个水钟吗？
Do you find it pleasing, my lord?
是的，非常喜欢
Oh, yes. Very.
雅典制造的
It was made here in Athens.
没有罗马的实用
Not as practical as our Roman ones, of course.
凡事求美是希腊人要命的缺点
The Greeks have such a weakness for beauty.
晚餐不合你心意吗？
Does the dinner not please you, my lord?
不是，只是我不饿
Very much. I'm not particularly hungry.
什么事能让你较开心呢？
If anything would please you more--
我已经很开心了，屋大维雅
Believe me, I am pleased.
你已经尽力
The gods know you do nothing but please me...
讨我欢心
...in every way.
多米提斯有消息吗？
Word from Domitius?
他被挡在城门外
He never even reached the palace.
不能进入皇宫
He was not permitted through the city gate.
恕我失陪
If I may be excused.
你不必回避
There's no need for you to go.
每次听到男人讨论国事
When I hear matters of state discussed by men...
总是担心着
...invariably I find myself wondering about...
酒怎么会变酸
...why the wine has gone sour.
晚安，鲁非欧
Good night, Rufio.
晚安，阁下
Good night, my lord.
多米提斯被拒于城外
Domitius turned away at the gate.
第几个了？
That makes how many?
今年第五个使者被拒
Five of your ambassadors turned away within this year.
若你照我的意思前往…
-If you'd gone when-- -It was the only favor I ever asked of you.
你答应过我的请求
You granted it.
与埃及的协约要尽快签订 很久没有黄金和粮食运来了
The treaty with Egypt must be made. We've received no wheat, no gold--
我不能前去与她谈判
I cannot go to her to negotiate a treaty!
她只肯跟你谈
She'll have no one else.
若连我
And what if she should...
也被拒呢？
...turn me away?
不可能吧
That would be quite impossible.
你对她真的没有感情了吗？
Have you ever really left her?
不
No.
我已经等了三天 要跟你单独谈谈
Three days I've waited for an audience with you alone.
谈什么？
What is the purpose?
全部出去，我要跟殿下私下谈
Get out, all of you. I'll see her privately.
- 你站的地方是埃及圣殿 - 我知道这是哪儿！
-You're before the throne of Egypt. -I know where I am!
那么请说出你的目的
State your purpose!
我不想公开讨论
Matters I won't discuss publicly.
我不与不明人士私下谈判
I do not grant private audiences to unidentified persons.
我是马克安东尼
I am Marcus Antonius.
我知道你是谁 但你现在的身分是什么？
I know who you are. What are you, at the moment?
罗马帝国统治者之一兼大使 主掌意大利以东的领土
Envoy of Rome, proconsul of all the Roman Empire to the east of Italy.
好吓人的头衔
An impressive title.
值得私下会谈了吗？
Worthy, perhaps, of a private audience?
但若不与埃及签订条约
Without a treaty of alliance with Egypt...
你无法统治你的领土吧？
...you could not hold the territories under your command. True?
可能
Possibly.
那么你是来求我的
Then, Lord Antony, you come before me as a suppliant.
你要是这么想，我也没办法
-If you choose to regard me as such. -I do.
哀求者该有哀求者的姿态
You will therefore assume the position of a suppliant before this throne.
跪下！
You will kneel.
- 什么？ - 下跪
-I will what? -On your knees.
你竟敢要罗马帝国三巨头之一…
You dare ask the proconsul of the Roman Empire--
我也要求过朱利斯凯撒
I asked it of Julius Caesar.
我命令你！
I demand it of you!
现在…
Now...
可以跟你签订条约
...you may have the treaty you asked for...
只要遵照以下条件
...on the following conditions:
以罗马三巨头之一的身分
By your authority as proconsul of Rome...
把犹太、约旦、阿美尼亚
...you will cede to Egypt immediately the following territories:
腓尼基、西奈、阿拉伯、塞浦路斯
Judea, Jordan, Armenia, Phoenicia, the provinces of Sinai and Arabia...
与克里特群岛割让给埃及
...the islands of Cyprus and Crete.
你要求的是三份一个罗马帝国！
You ask for one-third of the Roman Empire!
换句话说
Put it another way.
我给了你三份之二
I give to you two-thirds.
真慷慨…
Most generous.
我不能接受！
I cannot accept.
我建议你再考虑一下
I suggest you deliberate further.
或许跟罗马的上级商量商量
Perhaps consult with your superior in Rome.
上级？
My superior?
屋大维
Octavian.
凯撒屋大维啊！
Caesar Octavian?
还未叫你退下！
You have not been dismissed!
现在可以退下了
You are now dismissed.
全部出去，我要跟陛下密谈
Outside, all of you. Her Majesty and I will speak in private.
出去！不然杀了你们来喂马！
Out! Before I chop you up and feed you to my horses.
这就是罗马人吓小女孩的方法
That's how Romans frighten little girls.
他们喜欢吓小女孩，出去吧
They like to frighten little girls. Wait outside.
我之所以娶屋大维雅 是因为她哥哥坚持…
I married Octavia at her brother's insistence...
以这样来示好确保和平的权宜之策
...as a gesture of faith, of peace. A bargain sealed.
权宜？洞房夜只跟新娘握手？
With a kiss? Or did you simply shake hands on your wedding night?
我还未到罗马群众已在欢庆这件婚事 教我如何拒绝？
Rome was celebrating the marriage even before I arrived. How could I refuse?
说不啊
By saying no.
对我的要求你不是一概说不吗？
As you have said no to all my demands.
你那些根本是无理的要求 打落水狗！
They're unreasonable! The kind laid down for a helpless enemy!
你还不算是落水狗呢
You're not helpless...yet.
我不能割让那些领土 那等于要我公然跟罗马决裂
I can't cede the territories. It would lead to a break between Rome and me.
这正是我的目的
Why do you think I asked for them?
这正中屋大维下怀
It would be playing into Octavian's hands, what he hopes for.
实为不智
It would not be wise!
何谓不智？
What is wise?
将罗马、意大利 和全世界拱手让给屋大维？
To hand over Rome, Italy, the world to Octavian?
公然对他卑躬屈膝？
To grovel publicly before his authority?
把他的妹妹抱上床
Take his sister to wed and to bed.
求他原谅你
As if to beg forgiveness...
沾上埃及荡妇？
...for having stayed so long with your Egyptian harlot.
哪件事让你生那么大的气？ 与屋大维讲和？
What has angered you? That I dealt with Octavian how I could...
还是与他妹妹结婚？ 忌妒还是政治手段？
...or that I married his sister to do it? Jealousy or politics? Which?
都是！而且你对两者都懵然不知！
Both! And damn you for not understanding either.
不用你来教训我
I wouldn't look to you for instruction.
所以你像奴隶一样 乖乖的让屋大维扣上枷锁
Which is why you have come back chained to Octavian like a slave.
- 奴隶？ - 这枷锁也颇精致
-Slave! -And with such exquisite chains.
轻声细语，三从四德
So softly spoken, so virtuous.
听说她睡觉时裹得紧紧的
She sleeps, I hear, fully clothed.
我回来了，这不是已说明一切？
I come back. That's all that should concern you.
真的吗？
Should it?
主人一声召唤 你还不是回到他或她身边！
How long before your master snaps his finger and you run back to him, or her?
我只有一个主人
I have only one master.
我对你的爱
My love for you.
不
No.
你的主人从来就不是爱
Your master must not be love.
从来就不是爱
Never love.
有了爱，你就忘了一切
Give yourself to love and you give yourself to forgetfulness...
忘了身分，忘了雄心壮志
...of what you are and who you are and what you want.
你要的不只这些？
And what you want is worth so much more?
我不要爱来当我的主人
I will not have love as my master.
- 那就不爱！ - 也不要屋大维当主人
-Then you will not have love. -Nor will I have Octavian.
- 不需要害怕 - 看你说得颇有自信
-Never fear. -How confident you are.
那，屋大维的主人是什么？
And has Octavian a master?
他的野心，当罗马的皇帝和神
His ambition: to rule the Roman world as emperor and god.
就是罗马的天下
The Roman world, to begin with.
他的阻碍又是什么？
And what stands in his way?
- 你和我 - 和我儿子
-You and I. -And my son!
凯撒的法定继承人
The rightful heir to the name and glory of great Caesar.
但被屋大维篡夺了
Octavian has already stolen those and he will now destroy...
现在他要利用他妹妹… 毁掉罗马人对你的爱戴
...in the name of his sister, the love Rome has for you.
你跟她结婚
And by your marriage to her...
我就成了你的娼妇
...he has made of me, unmistakably, your whore.
不要怕屋大维？
Never fear Octavian?
不怕的人是他
It is he, now, who I think must be unafraid.
攻城掠地是我的专长
Show me a city and I'll tell you how to take it.
骁勇善战是我的本领
I'll find an army's weak points and hit them hard where they are.
但要我坐下来咬耳朵
But make me to sit down and talk in whispers of this and that...
谈论是与非，我真的不在行
...with an emphasis here and a shrug there, and I'm soon confounded and defeated.
依我的专长发挥
Meaning to do the best...
才能所向无敌
...I suppose I could not have done worse.
还赶得及
There is still time.
若问我的心愿
Let someone ask me what I want:
只想与世无争跟你住在这里
To live with you in peace and love.
全面投降
Do you have...
你有什么条件？
...conditions for total surrender?
跟凯撒一样
First, as did Caesar...
按照埃及礼仪跟我结婚
...you will marry me according to Egyptian ritual.
这不是条件是恩赐
That's not a condition, that's a reward.
你宣布凯撒里奥
You'll declare, by your authority...
成为埃及国王
...Caesarion to be king of Egypt...
我们以他的名义共同执政
...and we will rule together in his name.
绝对同意
Happily granted.
我提过的领土都割让给埃及
You will cede to Egypt all the territories I have demanded.
必须这样！
You must.
即使只为确保你的权力与地位
If only to assert your own authority and power.
否则，我们迟早一无所有
Otherwise, inevitably, in time we will lose everything.
你看不出来吗？
Can't you see that?
我眼中
I can see nothing...
只看到你
...but you.
我无法再原谅安东尼！
I am no longer content to forgive Antony!
根据蛮族礼仪娶个埃及人
To marry this Egyptian according to their barbaric rites!
罗马法例不会承认！ 当初凯撒自己…
Meaningless under Roman law! Great Caesar himself--
安东尼想有样学样
Yes. Bit by bit, Antony crawls behind his memory.
但请问朱曼尼卡斯…
But tell us this, Germanicus:
凯撒有没有将三份一个罗马帝国…
Did great Caesar also toss one-third of the Roman Empire...
送到克莉奥佩特拉怀里？
...into Cleopatra's undoubtedly deserving lap?
当年凯撒占领的地方 今日主权仍争论不休
The territories in dispute were subjugated by Julius Caesar.
凯撒之子应该有合法统治权
The right to rule over them is the heritage of his son.
依凯撒之名我赐予托勒密凯撒里奥
And in the name of the mighty Caesar I grant to King Ptolemy Caesarion...
这个权利
...that right.
让世人了解罗马的伟大
Let it be known the greatness of Rome lies not in what she takes...
在给予而不在侵占
...but in what she gives.
他说，罗马的伟大在给予
"Rome's greatness lies in what she gives," he says.
轻轻松松慷他人之慨
Then calmly gives what is not his.
克莉奥佩特拉
And Cleopatra takes...
予取予求下去
...and will take more.
战祸终将来临
And war will come.
她知，我知
She knows and I know...
难免一战
...that war will come.
但我不主战
But I will not speak for it...
也不与安东尼为敌
...nor will I speak against Antony.
我将等待被逼上战场
I must be forced into war.
罗马人民会逼我开战
The people of Rome must force this war upon me.
我要等民愤涌进元老院
They must storm the doors of the Senate, crying for it.
行动快的话，在罗马人知道之前
If we move quickly, the Romans won't know we've crossed the Mediterranean...
我们已越过地中海登陆希腊了
...until we land in Greece.
你和鲁非欧将军立刻上船
You and General Rufio will start embarking the troops at once.
是的，陛下
Yes, Your Majesty.
如果决定将敌军引入希腊…
If it is decided to move our armies into Greece.
已经决定了
It has been decided.
我的手下
My men do not...
不擅航海
...travel well by sea.
他们专长打陆战，在陆上行军
They fight on land. They move on land.
你的手下要听从我的指挥
Your men will do as they are told, as mine will.
我手下仍听我指挥！他们还不是…
My men will do as they're told by me. They have not yet become--
他们还是罗马人
They are still Roman.
但是
However...
我只知听命行事
...since I do as I'm told....
最终决定权还是在安东尼阁下
The final decision will, of course, be Lord Antony's.
相信你很快会作出定夺
And I'm sure that in time he will make it.
退下
That is all.
当着各军官面前 你最好不要和我争执
It would be wiser not to disagree in the presence of our officers.
你的军官们
Your officers.
你到底要我做什么定夺？
What final decision have you decided I am to make?
为什么反对调兵去希腊？
Why do you oppose transporting our armies to Greece?
我不想和罗马开战
Because I do not want war against Rome.
马克安东尼带领十万军队
One hundred thousand men led by Marc Antony.
屋大维不笨，他不会开战
Octavian is no fool. He won't fight.
他不想，但他不得不… 就在登陆的地点，会立即开战
He'll have to, instantly, on the spot where they land.
罗马不会对你宣战！
Rome will not declare war against you.
我不同意
I do not agree.
我没有征询你的意见！
I have not asked for your opinion.
至少现在没有
Not for some time.
见到三百艘新造的战舰就不同了
Not since I doubted the necessity of building 300 ships.
备战的目的是停战
The way to prevent war is to be ready for it.
建三百艘战舰而不打仗？
Have 300 warships ever been built for war without war?
不打仗一样可以整顿军容啊！
We shall have what we want without it.
陛下，请听我说
Your Majesty, please hear me.
我相信战事已是箭在弦上
I think we are very near the edge.
拉弓的人不是我们
Strings are being pulled, and not by us.
我们毫无选择正被操控
We are being managed and maneuvered without our choosing.
屋大维雅派来的代表
The deputation sent on behalf of Lady Octavia...
是在罗马极受敬重的人士
...chosen from the most highly revered men of Rome.
他们所能带回罗马的全是安东尼的…
Why? They can take back to their people nothing but Lord Antony's...
倔辱与及一纸不必要的休书
...forgive me, insulting and unnecessary divorce of her...
以及他的避而不见
...and his rejection of them.
我下的命令，我负责
It was done at my bidding. The responsibility is mine.
但做此事的人是我
The doing was mine.
你有何建议？
What do you propose?
我去罗马，尽量和屋大维及人民沟通
Let me go to Rome and approach Octavian, possibly the Roman people...
使他们相信我们爱好和平
...and assure them that we want peace.
去啊
Go then.
去罗马啊
Go to Rome.
保重
Sosigenes!
Take care.
那老人是个忠臣
He's very dear to you, that old man.
你的担忧写在脸上
Your concern and worry are written all over you.
对不起，但你流露出关怀的神情
Forgive me, but it's a kind of love that you're showing.
就等他们照 自己的意思去说吧，去谈判吧
Let them talk. Let them negotiate all they want.
时间站在我们这边 我们只会愈来愈强大
Time is on our side. We can only grow stronger.
议事堂内
These walls must not believe their ears...
竟这样一片死寂
...to hear such silence...
右边鸦雀无声
...from the right...
左边也鸦雀无声
...from the left.
人民的怒吼清晰可闻
The call of the Roman people can be clearly heard...
元老院各位大官
...yet the Roman Senate...
却毫无反应
...has no answer.
那么，我们就这样静静坐着
Shall we then just sit...
并听着
...and listen?
奥古斯都凯撒，我们都愿意 向克莉奥佩特拉宣战…
There is not one of us that would not willingly make war upon Cleopatra.
怎样宣战？
But how...
同时却又想避开向深受罗马爱戴
...without also making war upon Marc Antony...
而又深爱罗马的马克安东尼宣战
...loved by Rome and loving Rome?
受罗马爱戴，也深爱罗马…
"Loved by Rome and loving Rome."
我手上有一份安东尼最新的遗嘱
I have here the last will and testament...
听听他怎样爱罗马
...of Antony, who so loves Rome.
你们自己看
Read for yourselves...
他怎样爱罗马！
...how dearly Antony loves you, loves Rome...
他亲笔签署的最新遗嘱
...in this, his last will under his seal.
最近才由埃及送来
Only lately brought from Egypt...
放于圣殿 安东尼指示
...and deposited in our holy temple at Antony's request...
受人尊敬的西索吉尼斯做的
...by the distinguished Sosigenes.
超凡之人所做超凡的事
An extraordinary mission for an extraordinary man.
多么有智慧，多么切合 克莉奥佩特拉的心意，多么受她信赖
So wise, so close to Cleopatra, so trusted by her.
看啊！ 最终列入了…
Read in Antony's will...
安东尼的遗嘱
...at the end.
不要忘记你心爱的安东尼 的最终要求
Commit to memory the last request of your beloved Antony.
那是他对罗马爱的见证！
It bears witness to his love for Rome.
当他死时，里头说…
When he is dead, it says...
当马克安东尼死时…
...when Marc Antony has died...
他希望被葬在…
...it is his wish to be buried...
他挚爱的亚历山卓！
...in his beloved Alexandria!
在埃及
In Egypt!
与埃及人一起
Among Egyptians.
紧靠他的埃及娼妇！
Beside his Egyptian whore!
我说的是否事实？
Is what I say the truth?
我说的难道不是事实吗？
Do I speak the truth?
宣战！宣战！
-War! -War!
宣战！宣战！宣战！宣战！…
War! War! War!
各位眼前的是战争的金矛
I hold before you the Golden Spear of War.
元老院无反对
Placed into my hands without dissent...
授权落于我手中
...by the command and will of the Senate of Rome.
现在轮到各位 罗马子民来指引我
And now it is you, the people of Rome, who must direct me.
敌人在哪里？
Where is the enemy?
埃及在哪里？告诉我！
Where is Egypt? Show me the way!
不！
No!
是那里！
There!
埃及在那里！
There is Egypt.
于是，罗马人再次自相残杀
And so once more, the Romans warred upon each other.
就好像安东尼索预言…
And just as Antony had foretold...
屋大维的军队
...the forces of Octavian came to meet them...
开到登陆的地点
...on the spot where they landed...
就在希腊的爱克提安
...which was at Actium, in Greece.
明天日出决一死战
Action begins with the rise of the sun.
你的战略扼要凶猛但适合陆战
Your plan is brave and simple. It's possible on land...
打海战就显得不智
...but we debate its wisdom upon the sea.
敌军以海犯陆，且以寡敌众
I have an enemy on land with fewer troops, on sea with fewer ships.
看他怎样发挥他的智慧！
Let him debate the wisdom of his position.
我可以选择陆战或海战 而我选择了海战！
I have a happy choice. To destroy him wet or dry. I have chosen wet.
尤法诺，到女王船上汇报军情
I think it best, Euphranor, you report to Cleopatra aboard her vessel in the harbor.
你可以找一百个藉口
There you may point out to her...
向她说明我的方法不可行
...the reasons why my brave simplicity has failed.
但我首先废除你指挥的职务
In any case, you are relieved of your battle command.
你何时决定把所有战力…
This final commitment of yourself, your ships, of all of us...
用在海上与屋大维决一雌雄？
...to fight at sea, when did you decide?
- 对不起，鲁非欧，我不得不… - 坎尼迪斯和我几个月以来…
-Forgive me. I had-- -We've worked hard for many months.
训练了一支来自二十几个国家 将近二十万人的部队
We've trained an army of 200,000 men from 20 countries.
- 不会浪费的，战胜之后… - 二十万步兵和骑兵
-They won't be wasted-- -Of which, tonight, 20,000 of them...
挤在船上 拖到海上，承受风浪之苦！
...will be herded onto those ships and dragged out to sea, puking and afraid.
- 这是什么理论？ - 因为我军令如山
-Why, my lord? Why? -Because I have decided it will be so!
我认为这是种荣耀
I consider it an honor...
可以和安东尼阁下 在任何地方并肩作战
...to fight beside Lord Antony at any time, anywhere.
这才像罗马的口吻，拉莫斯
Spoken like a Roman, Ramos.
你代替鲁非欧，留在我身边
And you shall fight at my side, in Rufio's place.
鲁非欧，你留在女王船上
Rufio, you will remain with Her Majesty aboard her vessel.
遵命
As you command.
坎尼迪斯，你留在陆上
Canidius, you will remain with the land forces...
尽情隔山观虎斗
...cheering from the hilltop, if you like.
遵命
-As you command. -Exactly.
一定要遵从命令
As I command.
解散！
You're all dismissed.
安东尼！
Antony.
发生了什么事？
What has happened?
我吗？
To me?
你质问我发生什么事？
You have happened to me.
远处望到屋大维的战旗了吗？
Do the lookouts have Octavian's insignia?
- 日出就看见他的金鹰了 - 恐怕日落只剩一堆金羽毛
-A golden eagle. Sighted at sunrise. -By sunset we'll have those gold feathers.
令屋大维知道我们出来应战！
Let Octavian know we're coming!
让敌军见识我军的气势！
Let the enemy hear the voice of Antony's legions!
他在路上发个信号给凯撒
He's on his way. Signal my lord Caesar's ship.
安东尼有升起战旗吗？
Does it fly his insignia?
一定要严守我的命令！
My orders are to be followed exactly as issued.
愿主保佑安东尼不要改变战略
And may the gods grant that Antony has not changed his plan of battle.
他冲过去了
There he goes...
和从前打仗一样直扑中央
...as he's done 100 times on land. Straight for the center.
如果在陆地上我们可以保护侧翼
If only it were on land, and we were there to protect his flanks.
可惜我们不是
But we're not.
将所有部署向在女王船上的
This and all dispositions are to be signaled...
尤法诺汇报
...to Admiral Euphranor aboard Cleopatra's barge.
尤法诺？他不是负责指挥…
But Euphranor's in command of--
指挥模型玩具船
In command of moving toy ships on a painted ocean...
给女王了解最新的战况
...so that Egypt's queen can more clearly follow her war upon water...
打杖的是安东尼和两万罗马子弟兵
...to which she has committed Marc Antony and 20,000 Romans.
若真照他所讲的…
Just as he said he would.
安东尼和他的护航舰直扑屋大维
Antony and his escorts, by themselves, are after Octavian.
- 他已经突围到中央了 - 是他们让他进去的
-He's already broken through their center. -They let him through.
然后从旁包抄
They Roman line will close behind him.
若夹击战开始，他们就无法…
Not if we engage, as Antony said.
不会打夹击战的亚格里巴 会下令他们退后
They won't engage. Agrippa will pull them back and back, behind Antony...
安东尼追屋大维时他们一直跟在后面
...as Antony chases Octavian.
有什么最新战况？
What report?
安东尼已经穿过罗马中央战线
Lord Antony is already through the center of the Roman line.
为了追屋大维 他已经深入敌方舰群
He is now deep within the Roman fleet, in pursuit of Octavian.
快！快！
Faster! Faster!
他们加了速
They've increased their own speed. We're too heavy to catch them.
Then we'll slow them down.
准备开炮，炮手！
Start the ballistas. Javelin throwers.
瞄高一点，宁愿射过头
Aim high. Overshoot rather than under.
开炮！炮手！
Ballistas. Javelins.
开炮！
Ballistas!
屋大维的船比埃及的快很多
Octavian's ships are so much faster than our Egyptian tubs.
为什么亚格里巴不躲开？
Why doesn't Agrippa keep him away from Antony's ballistas?
炮手！
Ballistas!
Ballista!
炮手！
阁下！阁下！
My lord! My lord!
击中敌舰，摧毁一侧船桨！
A direct hit on the enemy! A bank of oars has been destroyed!
他从舷侧冲过来了！
He's coming around broadside.
准备碰撞！
We've got him!
撞他然后上船杀了他！
Collision course. We'll ram him, board and destroy him.
屋大维！
Octavian!
屋大维！ 你追随凯撒的时候到了！
Octavian! Now is your time to be a Caesar!
- 他躲在哪里？ - 屋大维不在这艘船上
-Where is he hiding? -My Lord Octavian is not on board.
现在包围安东尼
And now we close the trap.
全力进攻！
Now we hit my Lord Antony with everything we have.
没有安东尼的消息？
No word of Lord Antony?
他该已制服了屋大维
By now he must have Octavian. You said he rammed Octavian's ship.
不是说他撞毁了屋大维的船吗？
It may be Lord Antony rammed a ship flying Octavian's insignia.
若那真的是屋大维的船…
But if it is Octavian's ship, if Octavian is on board--
就算安东尼杀了他 他仍被其他敌军包围
If he finds and kills Octavian, he's still surrounded by the Roman fleet.
- 派遣支援部队！ - 没有支援部队！
-Then send him help. -I've none to send.
他们截断我们的舰队
They're pulling our ships apart now.
安东尼孤军作战
They've got Antony alone and cut off...
像群野狗围攻受伤的熊！
...closing in on him like a pack of dogs on a wounded bear.
- 安东尼的船？ - 被击毁了
-Lord Antony's ship? -Gone.
- 屋大维的呢？ - 起火燃烧，无计可施
-And Octavian's ship? -Burning, helpless.
将军，你认为…
Would you say, admiral...
安东尼是否已阵亡？
...that Lord Antony is dead?
返回埃及的话，风向如何？
How is the wind for Egypt?
很好
Fair.
立刻回航
We'll sail at once.
划桨手就位！起锚！ 航向埃及！
Man the oar banks. Hoist anchor. We sail for Egypt!
坎尼迪斯阁下！
My Lord Canidius!
永远记住爱克提安一役…
Remember always, that after the battle of Actium...
屋大维、安东尼双双战死
...with Octavian dead and Antony dead...
胜利者
...you saw the victor...
却驾着金船逃之夭夭
...sail away on her golden barge.
克莉奥佩特拉走了…
She's going.
Cleopatra's going!
丢低我们！
Leaving me!
阁下
My lord.
我军伤亡惨重 盔甲所余无几
My lord, our casualties are heavy. We have little armor left.
部队需要重组、打气
Our men need regrouping, someone to give them courage.
伤兵哀号，残存的需要支援
The dying are calling for you. The living need your help.
不能丢下他们不理…
You can't leave them.
听我说！
Listen to me!
救命！
Help!
凯撒，好消息！
Caesar, news!
克莉奥佩特拉走了 安东尼追在后面
Great news! Cleopatra is leaving the battle. Antony is following her.
我们大获全胜！
We have won a great victory.
停桨！
Weigh oars!
陛下正急于见你，请下去
Her Majesty is most anxious to see you. Will you come below?
抑或是你留在这儿 我请她上来？
Perhaps if you wish to remain here, she will come to you.
要不要准备食物？酒？
Shall I send you food? Wine?
陛下的命令
Her Majesty's orders.
她怕你
She's afraid you might...
伤害自己
...harm yourself.
请坐
Please.
屋大维越过叙利亚进入埃及
Octavian has crossed from Syria into Egypt.
几星期后会到达这里
He can be here in a matter of weeks.
亚历山卓只余下两个部队
There are two full legions here in Alexandria...
肯听命于你
...who have remained loyal to you.
他们等着…
They and their officers...
你下令
...are waiting for you to command them.
若不要与我说话 至少跟鲁非欧谈谈？
If not to me, won't you speak to Rufio at least...
或是找个你肯开口的人？
...or to anyone you choose?
安东尼，只等你一声令下！
Antony, just say what you want done and it will be.
你很久没望我了
It's been so long since you've looked at me. Don't turn away...
别转过头去
...even like this...
你的眼中充满了仇恨
...with your eyes filled with hate.
燃烧着怒火
How they burn with hate.
为什么？安东尼，为什么？
Why, Antony? Why?
因为我逃走？
Because I ran away?
他们说你已阵亡！
They told me you were dead!
那我
What...
还能怎样？
...could I do?
你突然消失了
Where could I go...
我还能去哪儿？
...in a world suddenly without you...
除了我的儿子和我的国家
...except to my son and my country...
凯撒里奥和埃及
...Caesarion and Egypt?
我要保护他们对抗屋大维
I wanted to save them from Octavian.
你也会想我逃走的
You would have wanted me to go.
你会命令我逃走的
You would have commanded me to go.
告诉我你会这么做！
Tell me you would have!
他们告诉我你已经阵亡了！
They told me you were dead.
他们说得对
You were quite right.
我已经死了
I am dead.
盖尔斯朱利斯凯撒
The armies of Gaius Julius Caesar...
一直向亚历山卓前来
...are advancing without opposition upon Alexandria.
盖尔斯朱利斯凯撒？
Gaius Julius Caesar?
屋大维篡夺了他的全名！
So now Octavian has stolen all of the name.
凯撒阁下希望转达 他对女王毫无偏见
Caesar wishes it known he has no quarrel with Cleopatra of Egypt.
那就叫他打道回府啊
Then let him take his armies out of here and go home.
战争或和平
He has charged me to say that the choice of war or peace...
由埃及自行抉择
...now rests with Egypt.
至于他，他诚心希望和平
And that for himself, he desires only peace.
他无条件讲和的要求是什么？
And what are his terms for this unconditional peace?
一份小小的纪念品…
A small token.
以表示一点心意…
A demonstration. A gesture.
代表克莉奥佩特拉女王的诚意
An indication of Queen Cleopatra's goodwill and good faith.
屋大维到底要什么？
What does Octavian want?
马克安东尼
Marc Antony.
安东尼
The...
颈上的人头？
...head of Marc Antony?
这个给他，作为我的答案
Take this to him as my answer.
埃及人很慷慨
Egyptian generosity.
屋大维要一个人头，我给他一对
Octavian may have two heads for the price of one.
要便要两个
Either two...
否则一个也没有
...or none.
听说你来这儿睡觉
I'm told you come here to sleep.
不是睡觉
Not to sleep.
是度过漫漫长夜？
To pass the night then.
我并不寂寞
I'm not alone.
老人家与我交换历史
The old boy and I exchange memories of life.
等于同屋主…或该说同墓主
It's like having a roommate, or should I say, "tomb-mate"?
若凯撒是你，他可会躲在这儿
If he were in your place, would I find Caesar here?
身边只有月光和顾影自怜？
Hidden away, wrapped in moonlight and endless self-pity?
又是自怜？找个新说法吧！
Self-pity again! You repeat yourself! Find new reproaches!
你只是借酒装疯
Until now it has just been a part of your being drunk.
为安东尼大唱悲歌
Singing sad songs for Antony.
时间应该用来与屋大维谈判
Your time would be better spent negotiating with Octavian.
把我的头交给亚格里巴吧 反正我也没什么损失
Why did you not give my head to Agrippa? It's no great loss to me.
听闻死第二次是不会痛的 还可以为你带来利益
Dying the second time is painless and possibly an advantage to you.
或许能与罗马重缔盟约
The basis, perhaps, of a great new alliance with Rome.
我不想跟罗马重缔盟约
I do not want a great new alliance with Rome.
那你要什么？
What do you want?
我是来找马克安东尼的
I have come for Marc Antony.
你的残兵、鲁非欧、我两母子
What is left of his army, Rufio, my son and I...
和全埃及都在等他
...all of Egypt are waiting for him.
时间无多了
There is little time.
马克安东尼？
Marc Antony?
这里没这个人
There is no one here by that name...
这活人
...alive.
什么时候？
Time for what?
等安东尼身穿盔甲
For Marc Antony to appear in shiny armor...
双手握剑
...swords flashing in both hands?
亚格里巴、屋大维
Agrippa. Octavian.
站远些！ 庆祝吧！救世主安东尼来了！
Stand back! Rejoice! Marc Antony will save the day!
你说安东尼？
Antony, you say?
他死于爱克提安
He died at Actium...
他逃走了
...running away.
他想在水面行走
He tried to run on the water, the story goes...
但你拒绝扶他一把
...but you weren't there to hold his hand!
鲁非欧…我的部下…
Rufio, my legions, waiting.
他们在等什么？
For what?
等我问他们对我的看法
To ask me what they carry in their eyes...
还是我自己对自己的看法？
...in their hearts, in their sleep, as I have in mine.
为什么你不壮烈牺牲？
Why are you not dead?
为什么不躲在深深的海底？
Why do you live? How can you live?
为什么
Why do you not lie in the deepest hole of the sea...
不光荣的战死？
...bloodless and bloated and at peace with honorable death?
你因为逃跑而求我原谅
You begged forgiveness from me for running away.
以母亲、一国之君的 身分向我哭诉原因
You wept and gave your reason. A mother to her child, a queen to her country.
但我能向谁哭诉，求谁谅解？
Where and how can I weep and beg? From whom?
谁？向千千万万死去的同袍？
The thousands and thousands who can no longer hear me?
我该解释吗？
Shall I give my reason?
还是简单一句：因为爱？
Shall I say simply, I loved?
当我看见你逃走时 我失去所有知觉
When I saw you go, I saw nothing.
只关心你走了…
Felt, heard, thought nothing except your going.
不理同袍生死 不关心埃及或罗马
Not the dying and dead, not Rome, not Egypt...
不理胜败、荣誉 羞辱朋友敌人、过去未来
...not victory or defeat, honor or disgrace...
只关心我的爱人走了 我一定要追随她
...only that my love was going and I must be with her.
我的爱，我的主人在呼唤！
That my love, my master, called.
我只能紧紧追随
And I followed.
直到那时…
And that only then...
我回头…
...I looked back...
了解…
...and I saw.
你以前说得多么正确
How right you were.
假如爱…
"Have as your master anyone, anything...
从不是你的主人
...but never love."
我错了
How wrong.
大错特错
How wrong I was.
安东尼，你追随的爱在这里
Antony, the love you followed is here.
作为对罗马帝国的献礼？
To be had upon payment of an empire.
没有你
Without you, Antony...
我不想活在这世上
...this is not a world I want to live in...
更别论东征西讨了
...much less conquer.
因为世上
Because for me...
再也找不到爱
...there would be no love anywhere.
你想的话，我陪你一齐死
Do you want me to die with you? I will.
还是你愿意与我活下去？
Or do you want me to live with you?
那要看你如何抉择
Whatever you choose.
选择活下去…会否太迟了？
Are we too late, do you think, if we choose to live?
永远
Better too late...
也不嫌迟
...than never.
城里流传一个恐怖的传闻
My lady, there is disturbing news from the city.
有人吓得离开了家园
The people are frightened. Some are beginning to leave their homes.
有人在晚上到处张贴传单
During the night, hundreds of notices were secretly posted everywhere.
早上发现被贴在市集
They were found stuck up in the marketplace.
甚至庙墙上也有涂鸦
Even painted on temples and other holy places.
署名屋大维盖尔斯朱利斯凯撒
Signed by Octavian Gaius Julius Caesar Augustus...
答应只要投降 就不会受伤害
...promising the Egyptian people peace if they surrender to him...
若不投降，就只有死路一条
...and destruction if they do not.
我已下令清除所有传单
I've had all of the notices removed and I've ordered the death penalty...
并将散播谣言 说安东尼的部队将谋反的人处死
...for anyone who spreads the false rumors that Antony's men might desert him.
若谣传属实，将处什么刑罚？
And what penalty if the rumors might come true?
你怎么知道？
How do you know?
我了解罗马人
I know the Romans.
只有一种将军不会被遗弃
There is only one commander they will never desert.
他的名字叫胜利
His name is "Victory."
但你才刚刚让安东尼离开似乎…
But yet, just now, you let Lord Antony go as if--
若你见过他，他一如以往
If you could have seen him, how proud he was...
气宇轩昂
...unafraid...
毫无惧色
...as he used to be.
我的部下都自由了吗？ 他们都离开了吗？
All of my attendants, have they been given their freedom? Have they gone?
还没有，他们还想再打扫一遍
Yes. They wanted once more to tidy up.
屋大维可以自己来打扫啊
Octavian can do his own housecleaning.
叫侍卫队长带三个精兵过来
The captain of the guards and three of his best men are to report to me...
现在先假扮成商人
...disguised as merchants.
保护凯撒里奥
They are to escort Caesarion out of Egypt...
离开埃及
...for the time being.
陛下，你自己呢？
And you?
请再三考虑
Your Majesty, please reconsider.
尤法诺有两艘快艇在东面港口
There are two of Euphranor's ships, very fast, in the east harbor.
将我包在地毯里带上船？
And would you roll me on board in a carpet?
不
No.
再也没有凯撒可以找了 至少我已找不到我的凯撒了
There are no more Caesars to go to, at least not for me.
- 那么你还是打算要… - 留在亚历山卓
-Then it is still your intention-- -To remain in Alexandria.
躲在最难找的地方
In the last possible place anyone would look.
躲在最没可能的地方
Literally, the last possible place.
陛下，我从不怀疑你的决定…
Your Majesty, I have never questioned your decisions.
现在不是讨论这问题的时候
This is not the time to begin.
让我留下来陪你
Let me stay with you.
夏蜜安和艾拉会照顾我
Charmian and Eiras will look after me.
万一安东尼回来…
If Lord Antony should--
安东尼回来时
When Lord Antony returns...
你到这里告诉他我的下落
...you will be here to tell him where to find me...
我等他
...waiting for him.
再一起想个…
Together, we will then do...
最好的办法
...what he thinks best.
听清楚了吗？
Is that clear?
- 清楚了 - 还有其他事吗？
-Yes, my lady. -Was there anything more?
我一直深爱着你
I have always loved you.
我早就知道了
And I have always known.
罗马从没见过这种军队！ 我们应该挑战整个亚洲
Rome has never known such an army. We should be taking on all of Asia.
屠杀安东尼的老弱残兵 简直是浪费时间
It seems a waste to slaughter what's left of Antony's army and Antony.
不会有屠杀，甚至不用流血
There will be no slaughter. I doubt there will be even bloodshed.
不费一兵一卒算打胜仗吗？我很怀疑
Has a battle ever been won without a blow being struck? I wonder.
我再重申一次
At any rate, let me make it clear once more.
要活捉安东尼 她也一样
I want Antony alive, and I want her alive.
我要留活口
She must be taken alive.
克莉奥佩特拉第二次到罗马
Queen Cleopatra's second procession into Rome...
盛况将胜过第一次
...will surpass her first.
你父亲给你的戒指…
The ring your father gave you.
现在
It is yours now...
交给你了
...to keep.
光荣骄傲的戴上它
Wear it with pride and with honor.
我很害怕…
I'm afraid.
虽然我知道我不应害怕
I know I shouldn't be.
谁说的？
Who told you that?
天下的国王
All kings...
特别是女王，都会害怕
...and especially queens, are afraid.
与其他人不同的是
They just manage not to show it.
我们会尽量掩饰
Something ordinary people cannot do.
敬你，安东尼！
Hail Antony!
- 离屋大维多远？ - 很近了，在山那边
-How near is Octavian? -Very near. Over that low ridge.
天黑后，他的营火会照亮天空
As it grows darker, the glow from his campfires will light up the sky.
我们的部队一定想看看
Our troops must find it attractive to watch.
对我们招手呢
Inviting, even.
安东尼的部队自己生火取暖
Antony's legions warm themselves at their own fires.
是啊
Yes.
骑马经过都觉得暖
I could feel the warmth as I rode by.
- 他有多少个军团？ - 二十个
-How many legions has he? -Twenty.
- 我们呢？ - 两个，是第十二军团，另一个是…
-And we? -Two. The 12th and one made up--
由各军团的残兵组成
Made up from what was left of the others.
我记得凯撒以两个军团打赢亚历山卓
As I remember it, Caesar held Alexandria with two.
鲁非欧，他们怎样部署？
How are they deployed? Rufio.
骑兵分置左右，中央是步兵
Cavalry to the left, cavalry to the right, infantry to the center.
另有三头大象虚张声势
Three elephants deployed to stamp out a fly.
屋大维和亚格里巴
My lords Octavian and Agrippa have all the strategic brilliance...
比小女孩更不懂战术
...of two vestal virgins.
我们退至这边地质较软的地方
We can draw back here to softer ground...
以瘫痪他的骑兵 然后与步兵决一死战
...too soft for cavalry and make our stand against their infantry.
决战？给他们踩扁？不！ 扣住大象
Stand? And let them stamp on us? No. Let the elephants stand.
我们打游击战
We flies will bite and buzz and tickle.
黎明第一道阳光升起时
At the first light of day...
趁屋大维的营火仍照亮天空
...while Octavian's glow still lights up the sky...
我们就发动攻击
...we will attack.
日落时，我军阵容将会加强
By sunset, both our loyal legions will have grown larger...
并更加忠心，我保证
...and even more loyal, I promise you.
晚安
Good night.
鲁非欧，吩咐卫兵
Rufio, tell the guards, please...
天亮前叫醒我
...I am to be awakened just before dawn.
当然
Of course.
鲁非欧
And, Rufio...
万一卫兵忘了或计错时间
...if, for whatever reason, the guards should forget or misjudge the time...
请你亲自来叫我
...will you, yourself, wake me?
卫兵会负责叫你
The guards will wake you.
- 万一呢？ - 那么我会来，不要怕
-But if they don't? -Then I will. Never fear.
我从来都不怕
I never fear.
再也不会怕了
Not anymore.
鲁非欧！
Rufio!
鲁非欧…
Rufio.
出手啊！
Fight!
出手啊…
为什么不出手？
Why don't you fight?
难道没一个人愿意成全安东尼
Is there no one who would grant Antony...
光荣战死的心愿？
...an honorable way to die?
在我之前…
Before me...
它的主人是位被罗马杀死的罗马人
...this was carried by another Roman killed by Rome.
另一位
Another...
凯撒
...Caesar.
不
No.
他跑不了的
We will have him.
等着一箭双雕吧！
We will have them both together.
她在哪儿？
Where is she?
陛下要我转告你
Her Majesty said to tell you...
她躲在最难找的地方
...she can be found in the last possible place anyone would look.
躲在最无可能的地方
Literally, the last possible place.
她可能在等我
She might have waited.
克莉奥佩特拉
Once more, it seems...
再次消失了踪影
...Cleopatra is out of reach...
我还是要紧随在后
...and I must hurry after.
终其一生
Throughout life...
甚至生命以外
...and now beyond.
一个女人，我唯一的爱
One woman, one love!
从未曾改变
Nothing changes...
至死不渝
...except life into death.
助我一臂之力
Will you help me?
请杀了我，阿波罗德斯！
Help me to die, Apollodorus!
我很想那样做
I want to!
但我不能！
But I can't.
我时常羡慕鲁非欧
I've always envied Rufio...
鲁非欧有对长手臂
...his long arms.
只有永远的…
The ultimate desertion:
背弃自己
I from myself.
否则我怎会错失 尽一生去追求的目标？
Else, how could I have missed what I must have aimed for all my life?
可以给我痛快一次吗？
Will you finish me now?
我的剑呢？请你了结我吧
Where is my sword? I beg you to finish me.
我骗你的，女王还在生
I lied to you. I let you think the queen is dead.
在陵寝里等你
But she's alive in her tomb, waiting for you.
克莉奥佩特拉在等我？
Cleopatra waiting?
你帮我
There will be just enough time...
还来得及
...if you'll help me.
把伤口紧紧绑住
Perhaps, my lady, if we were to bind his wounds tightly....
可能只会增加痛苦，让他睡吧
It would only give him pain. Let him sleep.
睡神
Sleep.
今晚请降临
Will you come tonight...
赐我一夜安眠
...so that I can sleep?
无尽黑夜的沉睡
The dark sleep.
他们终于见面了
They did meet after all...
相爱的人们
...the lovers.
他们会长伴左右
They will always meet.
为我活下去
Be lonely for me.
好的，但不能太久
But not for very long.
我保证
I promise.
一直以为我会…
I thought always I would die...
死得其所
...so well...
身为战士
...as becomes a soldier.
死得像个勇士
A soldier's death.
我以为我活得名符其实
I lived always as I saw fit.
其实名过其实
Unfittingly.
我想死后再来补偿
I would make it up, I thought, in death.
无论死后或生前
I expected--
我都…
I expected too much of me in death...
期望过高
...as in life.
你抱着我吗？
Are you holding me?
从来没有抱得那么紧
Never so closely.
再抱紧一点
Even closer.
我们一起证明
You and I will prove death...
死比相爱容易得多
...so much less than love.
你和我，我们会…
You and I, we will--
证明死…
We'll make of dying...
只不过是…
...nothing more than one...
最后的…
...last...
拥抱
...embrace.
吻我
A kiss...
封住我最后一口气
...to take my breath away.
世界从未…
There has never been...
如此寂静
...such a silence.
将他转过来
Turn him over.
古怪的民族毒药闻起来像香水
Strange people. Poisons that smell like perfume.
多找一点用重伤的人做试验
Find more. Have it analyzed. Test it on one of the badly wounded.
阁下，找到克莉奥佩特拉了
My lord, they have found Queen Cleopatra.
她将自己锁在陵墓里
She is locked in a building, that is to say, a tomb.
快
Hurry.
安东尼与她在一起，已经死了
Oh, Marc Antony is with her, they say. He's dead.
- 什么？ - 安东尼阁下死了
-What? -Lord Antony is dead.
就这样轻松地说出口吗？
Is that how one says it?
就这样轻松
As simply as that.
马克安东尼死了
Marc Antony is dead.
安东尼阁下死了
Lord Antony is dead.
就像说汤很热或汤凉了
The soup is hot. The soup is cold.
安东尼活着…安东尼死了
Antony is living. Antony is dead.
说这话时，你应吓得发抖！
Shake with terror when such words pass your lips...
如果有错，安东尼会割你的舌头
...for fear they be untrue and Antony cut out your tongue for the lie!
若真的如此
And if true...
则够你吹捧一辈子
...for your lifetime boast...
你三生有幸，宣布他的死亡
...that you were honored to speak his name even in death.
宣布这人的死
The dying of such a man...
应该哭喊
...must be shouted.
大叫
Screamed.
直到宇宙彼方传来回响
It must echo back from the corners of the universe.
安东尼已死！
Antony is dead!
罗马巨头马克安东尼气绝身亡！
Marc Antony of Rome lives no more!
凯撒面前，你无须低头
You needn't lower your head before Caesar.
我并未低头
I never did.
若他真的在此我会乐意低头
But if he were here, I'd be happy to.
我就是凯撒
I am Caesar.
随你高兴，屋大维
If it pleases you, Octavian.
看着我！
Look at me.
随你高兴
If it pleases you.
历尽沧桑、战乱…
After all this time and all that has happened...
你依旧明艳动人
...I suppose you are still beautiful, in a way.
多谢赞赏
You flatter me.
我是客观不带感情的说 别想歪了
My interest is impersonal. Should you have any intention--
现在你是在奉承自己
Now you flatter yourself.
战争结束了
The fighting is over.
你的国家、财产、以及你本人 都是我的战利品
Your country, your possessions and you are mine by right of conquest.
我准许你继续统治埃及 作为罗马的一省
I will permit you to rule Egypt as a Roman province and return your possessions.
只有一个条件 首先，你陪我回罗马
There is one condition. You will first accompany me to Rome.
跟在你的战车后面？
Behind your chariot?
看着我！
Look at me!
高傲的罗马人会否有耐心 在烈日下等几个小时
Would the proud citizens of Rome wait for hours in the hot sun...
看我的尸体被拖过广场？
...to see my dead body dragged through the Forum?
我会严密监视你
I'll have you closely watched.
屋太维雅…
Octavian...
当我决心一死
...when I am ready to die...
就一定会死
...I will die.
如果我答应你
What if I promise no harm will come to you...
丝毫无损的回亚历山卓呢？
...that you will be returned safely to Alexandria?
看着我！
Look at me!
你还可以要求什么？
What more could you ask?
你还没提到
You have not spoken...
我儿子
...of my son.
你儿子？我忘了
Your son. I'd forgotten him.
他在哪？
Where is he?
在安全的地方
Safe.
如果我答应你去罗马
If I go with you to Rome...
你肯让我儿子统治埃及？
...would you permit my son to rule Egypt?
我儿子的儿子…
And his sons?
世世代代统治下去
And theirs?
我尽力而为
I'll do everything I can.
这是罗马皇帝
Do I have your word...
和神的承诺？
...as a Roman emperor and god?
是的
Yes.
何时出发？
When will you require me to go?
尽快
As soon as possible.
我很疲倦 需要休息
At the moment, I am very tired and would like to rest.
请离开
If you'll leave me now.
你答应
Do I have your word...
不会自残？
...that you will not harm yourself in any way?
我以…
I swear it.
儿子的性命担保
On the life of my son.
卫兵一定要守在里面吗？
Must the guards remain inside?
我发过誓了
I have sworn...
用我儿子…
...after all...
担保
...on the life of my son.
现在，应该准备出发了
And now I must make ready to go.
没什么要准备的
There's little to do.
首先，我要吃饱
First, I shall want something to eat.
路上才有力气
Something to sustain me on my way.
水果可以吗？
Some fruit, perhaps?
拿来
Bring it to me.
夏蜜安！
Charmian.
艾拉，你拿
You then, Eiras.
你一直让我们跟在身边
You have never been without us.
不要留下我们
You cannot leave us behind.
或许…
Perhaps...
够我们三个一起
...there may be enough for us all.
拿张便条给我
Bring me a tablet to write on.
留言给屋大维
I want a message brought to Octavian.
留这给这种人是浪费
Words are wasted on such a man.
反正已经浪费了太多 在许多男人身上
I have wasted so many on so many men.
这是我最后一个请求
A few more. One last request.
你认为他会答应吗？
Will he grant it, do you think?
我不知道
I may never know.
既然如此
In this case...
我应该…
...I think I shall.
我会继续服侍陛下
I will serve Her Majesty as always.
一向是我服侍她
I have always served her.
两个都等着
You will both wait...
为我更衣
...to dress me for my travels.
我要穿第一次
I will wear--
跟安东尼见面时穿的服装
I want to be as Antony first saw me.
黄金制造的衣服
The dress of gold?
他一眼…
He must know at once...
就可以认出我
...even from a great distance...
就算距离很远也认得出来
...that it is I.
这是你的最后一项任务
This will be the last thing you do.
将这给门外的守卫转交屋大维
Drop this to one of the guards outside for Octavian.
但是要等过些时候
But be sure to wait.
现在来试试无花果该有的味道
And now let me see if the figs are as they should be.
听说这东西效果强烈
The taste of these, they say, is sharp...
而快速
...and swiftly over.
我多么清醒啊
How strangely awake I feel.
生命好像一场漫长的梦
As if living had been just a long dream.
别人的梦
Someone else's dream.
此时终于要结束了
Now finished at last.
现在
But then now...
应该开始…
...will begin...
我自己的梦了
...a dream of my own...
一场永不醒来的梦
...which will never end.
安东尼
Antony?
安东尼，等我
Antony, wait.
女王交给凯撒的讯息
From the Egyptian queen, a message for Caesar.
读出来，亚格里巴 抵达罗马的时候她的愿望将一一实现
Read it. Whatever she wants will be granted upon her arrival in Rome.
走在我座驾旁时再来讨论
We will discuss it as she walks beside my chariot.
写着什么？
What is it?
我唯一的愿望
"My one wish, which I implore you to grant...
是葬在安东尼身旁
...is to be buried at the site of Antony and to remain there...
直到天荒地老，永不分离
...until all things end."
她这样合乎高贵礼仪吗？
Was this well done of your lady?
极为高贵
Extremely well.
许多…
As befitting...
高贵的君主
...the last of so many noble...
最后都是如此
...rulers.
罗马人问道：
And the Roman asked:
这样做合乎高贵礼仪吗？
"Was this well done of your lady?"
婢女回答：
And the servant answered:
极为高贵
"Extremely well.
多高贵的君主
As befitting the last...
最后都是如此
...of so many noble rulers."